<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A booke of cookerie, otherwise called the good huswiues handmaid.]</title>
            <title>Book of cookery.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121381</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856564</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856564</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22136</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16381)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22136)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 548:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A booke of cookerie, otherwise called the good huswiues handmaid.]</title>
                  <title>Book of cookery.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 53, [3] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[E. Allde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Caption title, A3r reads: The good huswiues handmaid.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 13853.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 13853 on UMI microfilm reel 548.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cookery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="recipe_book">
            <pb facs="tcp:22136:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22136:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The good Huſwiues hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, for Cookerie in her Kitchin in dreſſing all maner of meat, with other wholſom diet, for her &amp; her houſhold. &amp;c.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boile mutton with mallowes or turneps.</head>
                  <p>TAke a necke of Mutton, cut it in rib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, and put it in a pot, and a good quantitie of beefe broth, and make it boyle: then take your Turneps or Mallowes, and cut them in peéces, of the bignes of your mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, then put into your pot a little pepper, and ſo let them ſtew till they be verie tender, then take them of and ſerue them vpon ſops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle mutton with Spinage.</head>
                  <p>TAke your necke of mutton and cutte it in peeces, and put it into a faire Potte, and a good quantitie of mutton broth, and make it boyle: then take ſwéet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>con, and cut it of the bignes of your fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>nd of the length, and put it in your pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n péeces: then take three good ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap> Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, waſh it verie cleane, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ing the water from it, and cut it ſmall, and put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:22136:2"/>the pot, and a litle pepper and ſalt, look that you haue no more broth then will couer your me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſo let it ſtewe verie ſoftly till it bee ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, then ſerue it vpon ſops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle mutton with Carrets.</head>
                  <p>TAke a breaſt or necke of Mutton cut it of the bignes of your thombe, and put it into an ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>then potte with faire water, and make it ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h: Then take Carret rootes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ape them cleane, and cutte them of the byg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your Mutton, and let them ſéeth, then put in halfe a handfull of ſtripped Tyme, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much of Sauorie and yſope, and a little ſalte and Pepper: Let them ſeeth till your Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and roots be verie tender then ſerue them vpon ſops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle mutton with Coleworts.</head>
                  <p>TAke a necke of fat Mutton, and cut your ribbes, and broyle them vpon a girdy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on till they bee halfe enough, then put them in a faire earthen pot, and a good quantitie of beefe broth and make them boyle: Then take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> handfull of Colewortes, and waſh them cleane, and beate them in péeces, and put th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>our Mutton, and a ladle full of the fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> beefe broth, and a little Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd ſo let them ſtewe till they be verie tender, and put them vpon Soppes,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22136:2"/>put no ſalt in till the meate be readie to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle a legge of mutton with a pudding.</head>
                  <p>FYrſt, with a knife raiſe the ſkin round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout till you come to the iointes, and when you haue perboyled the meate, ſhred it fine with ſuet or Marie, Parſley, Marioram, and Peniroyall: then ſeaſon it with Pepper and ſalte, cloues, Mace, and Sinamon, and take the yolkes of nine or tenne egges, and mingle with your meate a good handfull of Currans, and a fewe minced Dates, and put the meat into the ſkinne of the leg of Mutton, and cloſe it with prickes, and ſo boyle it with the Broth that you boyle a capon, and let it ſeeth the ſpace of two houres.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle a leg of mutton with Lemmons.</head>
                  <p>VVHen your Mutton is halfe boyled, take it vp, cut it in ſmall peeces: put it into a pipkin, and couer it cloſe, &amp; put thereto the beſt of the broth, as muche as ſhall couer your mutton, your Lemmons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſliced verie thin, and quartered, and Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, put in pepper groſſe beaten, and ſo let them boyle together, and when they bee well boyled, ſeaſon it with a little Vergious, ſugar,
<pb facs="tcp:22136:3"/>pepper groſſe beaten, and a litle Saunders, ſo lay it in fine diſhes vpon ſoppes. It will make three meſſe for the table.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle mutton with Endiue, Borage, or Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, or any kinde of hearbes that may ſerue thereunto.</head>
                  <p>VVHen your mutton is well boyled, take the beſt of the broth, and put it in a pipkin: and put thereto an handfull of endiue, borage, or what herbs you liſt, and caſt therto a few currans, and let them boyle well, and put thereto a peece of vpper cruſt of white bread, ſeaſon it with pepper groſſe beaten, and a litle vergious, and a little Suger, and ſo poure it vpon your meat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boile mutton for a ſicke bodie.</head>
                  <p>PVt your Mutton into a pipkin, ſeeth it, and ſcum it cleane, and put therto a cruſt of bread, Fenell roots parſly rootes, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans great raiſons (the ſtones taken out) and hearbs, according as the pacient is. If they bée cold, hot hearbes may be borne: if they be hot, cold hearbs be beſt, as Endiue, Sinamon, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olet leaues, and ſome Sorrell: let them boile together. Then put in Prunes, and a verie li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſalt. This is broth for a ſick bodie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make balles of mutton.</head>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:22136:3"/>
                  <p>TAke your Mutton &amp; mince it very fine with ſuet. Then ſeaſon it with ſugar ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Ginger, cloues and mace, Salt and rawe egges, make it in round balles. Let your broth ſéeth ere you put them in. Make your broth with Currans, Dates quartered, whole mace and Salt. Thicke it with yolks of Egges, and Vergious, and ſerue it vppon ſops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle a Capon with Orenges after Miſtres Duffelds way.</head>
                  <p>TAke a Capon and boyle it with veale, or with a marie bone, or what your fancy is. Then take a good quantitie of that broth, and put it in an earthen pot by it ſelfe, and put thereto a good handfull of Currans, and as manie Prunes, and a fewe whole ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſome Marie, and put to this broth a good quantitie of white Wine or of Clarret, and ſo let them ſeeth ſoftlye together: Then take your Orenges, and with a knife ſcrape of all the filthineſſe of the outſide of them. Then cut them in the middeſt, and wring out the iuyce of three or foure of them, put the iuyce into your broth with the reſt of your ſtuffe, then ſlice your Orenges thinne, and haue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the fire readie a ſkillet of faire ſeething water, and put your ſliced Orenges into the
<pb facs="tcp:22136:4"/>water, &amp; when that water is bitter, haue more readie, and ſo change them ſtill as long as you can finde the great bitterneſſe in the water, which will be ſixe or ſeauen times, or more, if you finde need: then take them from the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let that runne cleane from them: then put cloſe Orenges into your potte with your broth, and ſo let them ſtewe together till your Capon bee readie. Then make your ſops with this broth, and caſt on a little Sinamon, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and Sugar, and vpon this lay your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, and ſome of your Orenges vpon it, and ſome of your Marie, and towarde the ende of the boyling of your broth, put in a little Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, if you thinke beſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle a Capon in white broth.</head>
                  <p>BOyle your Capon in faire liquor, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it to keep it white, but you muſt boile no other meate with it, take the beſt of the broth, and as much Vergious as of the broth, if your vergious be not too ſowre, &amp; put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whole Mace, whole pepper and a good hand full of Endiue, Letuce or Borage, whether of them ye will, ſmal Raiſons, Dates, marow of marow bones, a little ſticke of Sinamon, the peele of an Orenge: then put in a good peece of Sugar, and boil them well together: then take two or three yolkes of egges ſodden, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22136:4"/>ſtrain them and thick it withal, and boil your prunes by themſelues, and lay vpon your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon: poure your broth vpon your capon.</p>
                  <p>Thus may you boyle anie thing in white broth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>An other way to boyle a capon in white broth.</head>
                  <p>TAke marow bones, breake them, and boile them and take out the Marrowe. Then ſeeth your capon in the ſame liquour. Then take the beſt of the liquour in a ſmall potte to make your broth withall, then take Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, Dates, and Prunes, and boile them in a potte by themſeiues, till they bee plum, then take them vp, and put them into your broth, then put whole Mace to them, and a good quantitie of beaten Ginger, and ſome Salte. Then put the Marrowe that you did take from the bones, and ſtraine the yolkes of Egs with Vineger, and put them into your Broth, with a good peece of Sugar, but after this it muſt not boile: then take bread, and cut there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thin ſippets, and lay them in the bottome of a diſh then take ſugar, and ſcrape it about the ſides of the diſh, and lay thereon your Capon, and the fruit vpon it, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boile a Capon in brewes.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22136:5"/>
                  <p>YOu muſt boyle your Capon with fatte meat, then take the beſt of the broth, and put it in a pipkin, and put whole mace to it, whole Pepper, ſome red Currans, halfe as much white Wine as you haue of broth, good ſtore of marrowe and Dates, and ſcum them cleane, and kéep your liquor verie clear, and ſeaſon it with vergious and Sugar, and then lay your Capon vpon browes finely cut, and ſo poure your broth vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle a Capon with Orenges or Lemmons.</head>
                  <p>TAke your Capon and boyle hint tender, and take a little of the broth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and put it into a Pipkin, with Mace and Sugar a good deale, and pare thrée Orrenges and pill them, and put them in your Pipkin, and boyle them a little among your broth, and thicken it with wine and yolks of egges, and Sugar a good deale, and ſalt but a little, and ſet your broth no more on the fire, for quai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and ſerue it in without ſippets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Sops for a Capon.</head>
                  <p>TAke toſtes of bread, Butter, Claret wine, and ſlices of Orenges, and lay them vpon the toſtes, and Sinamon, Sugar, and Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:22136:5"/>
                  <head>To make Sops for Chickens.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt take Butter, and melt it vpon a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingdiſh with coales, and laye in the diſh thinne toſtes of breade, and make Sorell ſauce with Vergious and Gooſeberries, ſeeth them with a little Vergious and lay them vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle a Mallard with cabage.</head>
                  <p>TAke the Cabage and pick them cleane, and waſh them, and perboile them in faire wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: then put them in a Colender, and let the water runne from them, then put them in a faire pot, and as much beefe broth as will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them, and the Marie of three Mary bones whole. Then take a Mallard, and with your knife, giue him a launce along vpon each ſide of the breaſt. Then take him of, and put him into your Cabage, and his dripping with him, for he muſt be roaſted halfe enough, and hys dripping ſaued, and ſo let him ſtewe the ſpace of one hower. Then put in ſome pepper and a little ſalt, &amp; ſerue in your Mallard vpon ſopps, and the Cabage about him, and of the vpper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of the broth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boile a mallard with Onions.</head>
                  <p>TAke a Mallard, roſt him halfe enough, and ſaue the dripping, then put him into a faire
<pb facs="tcp:22136:6"/>pot and his grauie with him, and put into his bellie ſixe or ſeuen whole Onions and a ſpoon full of whole pepper, and as much abroad in your pot, put to it as much Mutton broth or béefe broth as will couer the Mallarde, and halfe a diſh of ſwéete butter, two ſpoonefuls of Vergious, and let them boile the ſpace of an houre. Then put in ſome ſalt, and take off the pot, and laie the Mallard vpon ſoppes, and the Onions about him, and powre the vppermoſt of the broth vpon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle a Ducke.</head>
                  <p>SEeth the Ducke with ſome good Marrow bones, or Mutton, and take the beſt of the broth, and put therein a few Cloues, a good manie sliced Onions, and let them boile well together till the Onions bee tender, and then ſeaſon your broth with Vergious and a litle bruiſed pepper: Take vp your Ducke and laie it vpon ſops, and giue it two ſlices vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the breſt, and ſticke it full of Cloues, and powre the broth vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle Stockdoues.</head>
                  <p>SEeth them with béefe or mutton. Take the beſt of the broth, and put in a pipkin, and put thereunto Onions finely minced and a fewe Currans and ſo boile them till they be verie tender, and ſeaſon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22136:6"/>and a litle ſwéet butter, and powre them vpon your Stockdoues, when they be laid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle a Conie with a pudding in his bellie.</head>
                  <p>TAke your Conie and flea him, &amp; leaue on the eares, and waſh it faire and take gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bread, ſweet ſuet minced fine, Corrans, and ſome fine hearbes, Peniroiall, winter ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, Parſlie, Spinnage or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eetes, ſweete Marioram, and chop your hearbes fine, and ſeaſon it with Cloues, Mace and Suger, and a litle Creame, and ſalt, and yolkes of Egges, and Dates minced fine. Then mingle al your ſtuffe together, and put it into your rabbets bellie, and ſowe it vp with a thred. For the broth, take Mutton broth, when it is boyled a little, and put it in, then put in Gooſe berries or els Grapes, Currans, and ſwéete Butter, Vergious, ſalte, grated bread, and Sugar a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and when it is boyled, lay it in a diſh with ſops, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle Chickens or Capons.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt boyle them in faire water till they be tender: then take bread and ſtéepe it in the broth of them, and with the yolkes of foure or fiue Egges, and Vergious or white Wine, ſtraine it, and there with ſeaſon your
<pb facs="tcp:22136:7"/>broth and your Capon in it. Then take But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Parſlie, and other ſmall hearbs, and chop them into it. And ſo ſerue them foorth vppon ſoppes of bread.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle Chickins with a Cawdle.</head>
                  <p>TAke your chickens whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are fair ſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and truſſed and ſtuffed with Parſelie in their bellies, and put them in a potte with faire water and a little ſalt, and put to them twentie Prunes, halfe a handfull of Corrans and Raiſons, and let them boyle altogether till your Chickens be tender, then take ſixe yolkes, and a pinte of Vinegar, and ſtraine them together, and put thereto a quarterne of Sugar, or as yee thinke meete, and ſo let it boyle, but ye muſt ſtirre it ſtill, els it wil curd: and when it boyleth take it from the fire: then take your chickins, and put them in a colen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the broth may goe cleane away, and ſo put your chickens and the fruite into the cawdell, and make ſoppes, and lay on your chickens and the fruite, and powre on the cawdell.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſeeth chickens in Lettice.</head>
                  <p>TAke a necke of Mutton with a Marrowe bone, and ſo let it ſeeth and ſcumme it cleane, and let it boyle well together, and when it is enough, then take out ſome of it, and ſtraine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22136:7"/>it, and put in your chickens: then take a good many Lettuce, and waſh them cleane and put them in. Then take a litle white breade and ſtraine it, and put it into the pot to thicke it withall. Then put a litle whole mace to ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it, with Pepper and Vergious, and a litle Suger, and cut Sops, and lay them on, and put on the marrow, and ſo ſerue them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to boile chickens with hearbs.</head>
                  <p>TAke your Chickens and ſcalde them, and truſſe the wings on, and put then forte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wings of your chickens, and ſet them on in a litle pot and ſcumme them faire, when they haue boiled, put in Spinnage or Lettuce a good deale, and Roſemary, ſwéete Butter, Vergious, ſalt, and a litle Suger, and ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Bread with a litle wine, and cut ſippets and ſerue it out. So may you boile mutton, or Pigions or Conie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to ſeeth Hennes and Capons in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in white broth.</head>
                  <p>TAke a necke of mutton and a marrowe bone, and let them boile with the Hens together, then take Carret rootes and put them into the potte, and then ſtraine a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle bread to thicke the pot with all and not too thicke: ſeaſon it with Pepper and Vergious, and then couer them cloſe, and then let them
<pb facs="tcp:22136:8"/>boile together, then cut ſops and put the broth and the marrow aboue, and ſo ſerue them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle Calues feet or Lambs feet.</head>
                  <p>TAke your Calues feet after they be ſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, cut them in the middeſt, and put them into an earthen pot, &amp; put to them mutton broth aſmuch as wil couer them then take a litle Spinnage and Lettice, and a little ſtripped Time, and put it in your pot, and a diſhe of ſwéet butter, and a litle ſalt, and let them boyle till they be verie tender: and when ye be readie to ſerue them foorth, take the yolkes of thrée Egges, and almoſt a pinte of Vergious, and ſtirre them well together, and take your pot from the fire ſéething, and put in your Vergious and egges, and ſtirre it well, and ſerue them in vpon ſops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to boile a tripe.</head>
                  <p>TAke a Tripe and cut it in péeces, of the breadth and length of your finger, and put them in an earthen pot, &amp; put thereto as much Mutton broth as will couer them, a litle Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, Spinnage, a litle ſalt and Vergious, ſo let them ſtew ſoftly til they be verie tender, &amp; when yée will ſerue them in, caſt on a litle Pepper, and ſerue them on ſops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:22136:8"/>
                  <head>To boyle tripes, pigs petietots or Neates feet.</head>
                  <p>TAke your Neats féete, tripes, or petitoes, and cut them in ſmall péeces, and boile them with butter, Sinamon, Currans, and a litle vinigar, and ſerue them in vpon ſops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to boyle pigs petitoes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way.</head>
                  <p>BOyle them in a pint of Baſtard, and put thereto four Dates minced, with a few Corrans and a litle Time, chop the time ſmall, ſo let it boile, till it be wel: ſeaſon your pot with Sinamon, Ginger, ſalt, and a litle Vergious.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boyle Chickens after the French faſhion.</head>
                  <p>QVarter the Chickens in foure péeces: then take after the rate of a pinte of wine for two Chickens: then take time &amp; parſly as ſmall minced as ye can, and foure or fiue Dates, with the yolkes of foure hard Egges: and let this boile together, and when you will ſeaſon your pot, put in ſalt, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon and Ginger, and ſerue it foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To boile tripes after the French faſhion.</head>
                  <p>TAke a Tripe, and a fewe Onions, mince them ſmall together, and boyle them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb facs="tcp:22136:9"/>and ſeaſon your pot with a little Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Vinigre and ſalt, and ſo ſerue them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make long worts.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good quantitie of Colewortes and ſeeth them in water whole a good while, then take the fatteſt of powdered béefe broth, and put to the woortes, and let them ſéeth a good while after: then put them in a platter and lay your poudred béefe vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Triped mutton.</head>
                  <p>TAke a paunche of a Shéepe faire ſcowred, caſt it in a pot of boyling water, and ſcum it cleane and take vp the fat. Then take it and cut it in ſmall peeces of the breadth of twoo pence, and put it in a potte of ſtronge broth of Béefe or mutton, take Parſlie blades minced and put to it, and let it ſeeth. Then put in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Ginger, a litle Vergious, Saffron and ſalt, and let them boile together till it bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, ſo ſerue it foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to boyle a Lambs head and purtenance.</head>
                  <p>STrain your broth into a pipkin, and ſet it on the fire, and put in butter, and ſcum it as cleane as you can, and put in your meate, and put in Endiue, and cut it a litle and ſtraine a litle yeaſt, and put into it, and Currans, and Prunes, and put in all manner
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22136:9"/>of ſpices, and ſo ſerue it vpon ſops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to boile Quailes.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a pot with ſwéete broth and ſet them on the fire: then take a Carret roote, and cut him in péeces, and put into the pot: then take parſely with ſwéet hearbs, and chòp them a little, and put them into the pot: then take Sinamon, ginger, nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs and pepper, and put in a litle vergious, and ſo ſeaſon it with ſalt, ſerue them vpon ſops and garniſh them with fruite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to ſmere a Conie.</head>
                  <p>TAke the Liuers and boyle them, and chop it, and ſweet hearbs, apples, and the yolkes of hard Egges, and chop them altogether, and Currans, Sugar, Sinamon, Ginger, and parſley, and fill the Conie ful hereof, then put her into the ſweet broth, and put in ſweet but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then chop the yolkes of hard Egges, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Ginger, ſugar, and caſt it on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie when you ſerue it vp, ſeaſon it with ſalte, ſerue it on ſops, and garniſh it with fruit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Hodgepot.</head>
                  <p>BOyle a necke of Mutton, or a fat rumpe of Beef, and when it is well boyled, take the beſt of the broth, and put it into a pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, and put a good many Onions to it, two handfull of Marigold flowers, and a handfull
<pb facs="tcp:22136:10"/>of Parſley fine picked, and groſſe ſhred, and not too ſmall, and ſo boyle them in the broth, and thick it with ſtrained bread, putting ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in groſſe beaten pepper, and a ſpooneful of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigar: and let it boyle ſomewhat thicke, and ſo lay it vpon your meat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to a make Hodgepot in pots.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good peece of a leg of Mutton, pare away the ſkinne from the fleſh verie ſmall, and take halfe as much marrowe as you doe fleſh, &amp; then put them both into an earthen pot and put to it halfe a pint of beefe broth, or halfe a pint of Mutton broth that is not ſalt, and put thereto a Nutmeg beaten, and a litle pepper, two ſpoonefuls of currans, and twenty prunes and let them ſtewe ſoftlie vpon a ſoft fire, and ſtirre it well together often, or els it will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together in lumps: and when it hath ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an houre, put into it a ſpoonful of vergious and ſerue it vpon ſops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>The order to boyle a brawne.</head>
                  <p>TAke your Brawn, and when you haue cut him out, lay him in fayre water foure and twentie houres, and ſhift it foure or fiue tymes, and ſcrape and bind vp thoſe that you ſhall thinke good with hempe, and binde one handfull of greene Willowes together, and lay them in the bottome of the pan, and then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22136:10"/>put in your Brawne and ſcum it verie cleane, and let it boyle but ſoftly, and it muſt bee ſo tender that you may put a ſtraw through it, and when it is boyled enough, let it ſtand and coule in the pan, and when you take it vp, let it lye in Trayes one houre or two, and then make ſowſing drink with ale and water, and ſalt, and you muſt make it verie ſtrong, and ſo let it lie a weeke before you ſpend it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a good white broth.</head>
                  <p>TAke two marrow bones and a Cock, and boyle them together in faire water and white wine. Then take Parſley, Tyme, Spinnage &amp; Lettice, and bind them in a bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell, and put it in the pot with the water and wine, the Cock &amp; marrow bones. Then take Prunes and currans, &amp; binde them in a cloth, and put them in the potte, and a quantitie of whole mace, and binde them in like manner by themſelues, and put into the pot a peece of Butter, and a good quantitie of Sugar. When the Cocke and the mary bones be ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and readie to be ſerued: Then take from them the broth, and ſtraine it verie cleane, and put it into another pot. Then take the ſaid mace, Prunes and currans foorth of the clothes &amp; put them into the pot: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take three
<pb facs="tcp:22136:11"/>yolkes of Egs, and Roſewater, and put them into the broth, and boyle it a little while, fayre and ſoftlie with a litle ſalt, and ſo ſerue it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Farts of Portingale.</head>
                  <p>TAke a peece of a leg of Mutton, mince it ſmal and ſeaſon it with cloues, Mace pepper and ſalt, and Dates minced with currans: then roll it into round rolles, and ſo into little balles, and ſo boyle them in a little beefe broth and ſo ſerue them foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Fyſtes of Portingale.</head>
                  <p>TAke ſome ſwéet ſuet minced ſmall, the yolks of two egs, with grated bread and currans: temper al theſe together with a litle ſaffron, ſinamon, ginger, and a litle ſalt: then ſeeth them in a litle Baſtard or ſack a little while: and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue boiled a litle take it vp, and caſt ſome ſugar to it, &amp; ſo make bals of it as big as tennis balles, &amp; lay foure or fiue in a diſh, and powre on ſome of the broth that they were ſodden in, and ſo ſerue them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make French pottage.</head>
                  <p>TAke the ribs of Mutton, chop them ſmall the bones and all, with the fleſh in ſquare peeces. Then take Carret roots, and for lack of them, Onions, or both together and if you will, or els hearbes, ſuch as you like: ſeeth al theſe together, and when you will ſerue it in,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22136:11"/>ſeaſon your pot with a little Synamon, Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ſalt, and ſo ſerue it foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make fine pappe.</head>
                  <p>TAke Milke and flower ſtrain them, and ſet it ouer the fire till it boyle. Then take it off and let it coole, then take the yolkes of egs ſtraine them and put it in the milk, and ſome ſalt, and ſet it in the fyre, and ſtir it till it bee thicke, and let it not boyle fullie. Then put it in a diſh abroade, and ſerue it foorth for good pottage.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A broth for a weake bodie.</head>
                  <p>TAke a legge of Veale, and ſet it ouer the fyre in a gallon of water, and ſcum it clean and when you haue ſo doone, put in thrée quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of a pounde of currans, halfe a pound of prunes &amp; a good handfull of Borage, as much Langde beefe, as much of Mints, and as much of Harts tong, let all theſe ſeeth togeather till all the ſtrength of the fleſh be ſodden out: then ſtraine it as cleane as you can. And if ye think the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be in any heat, put in Violet leaues, or Succorie, as ye do with other hearbs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A good way to powder or barrell beefe.</head>
                  <p>TAke the beefe and lay it in mere ſawce a day &amp; a night. Then take out the béefe and lay it vpon a hirdle, and couer it cloſe with a ſheete, and let the hurdle be
<pb facs="tcp:22136:12"/>ſaid vpon a peuerell or couer to ſaue the mere ſauce that commeth from it: then ſeeth the brine, and lay in your Beefe againe, ſee the brine be colde ſo let it lye two dayes and one night: then take it out, &amp; lay it again on a hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del two or three dayes. Then wype it euerie peece with linnen cloth, dry them and couch it with ſalt, a laying of Beef and another of ſalt: and ye muſt lay a ſtick croſſe each way, ſo that the brine may run from the ſalt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to keep Lard after my Lord Ferries way.</head>
                  <p>SCald your hogge, and euen as you dreſſe your Bacon hogge, ſo dreſſe this: then lay it in ſalt, the ſpace of three weekes or a moneth. Then take it vp, and let it hang ther as in maner is no ſmoke: but when ye thinke it waxeth moyſt, let it be hanged ſo lowe that the heate of the fire may come to it: or els put it in an Ouen when the breade is drawne out, and when ye thinke it be wel dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, take it out againe til it waxe moyſt again, and ſo ye ſhal keepe it wel enough thrée quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of a yeare, and neuer take the leane from the fat but as ye occupie it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to keepe Larde after my Lady We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone Brownes way.</head>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:22136:12"/>
                  <p>FLea the fat Lard from the fleſh, and put in bay ſalt, ye muſt caſt a good deale vppon it, and euen ſo ſalt it, and roule it together round, and ſo put it in a heap of ſalt, and when ye will occupie any of it, cut of it as yee need, and lay it in water, and ſo ye may keepe it as long as ye will.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>The keeping of Lard after my Lady Marqueſſe Dorſets way.</head>
                  <p>TAke a fat hog and ſalt him, and when he is through cold, quarter him, and take all the bones and the fleſh from the fat: and then take the fat of the ſaid hog, and couch it in fayre dry white ſalt, and ſo keepe it two or thrée dayes: then change it again into faire drie white ſalt, euerie thirde or fourth day, and at the fourtéen daies end, take faire cold water and white ſalt and make a verie ſtrong brine, ſo that your brine be made ſo ſtrong that it will beare an egge almoſt cleane aboue the brine, and put it in a faire cloſe veſſell: then take the ſaid Lard and lay it in the ſaid brine, ſo that the brine co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it ouer: ſo change it into new brine euerie fourtéen daies, for the ſpace of ſixe weeks, and after that it needeth not to be changed. But the brine may not be made of wel water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Blaminger.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22136:13"/>
                  <p>TAke a Capon, boyle him in faire water ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie tender, then take the brawne of him &amp; chop it ſmall, then take Almones, and blanch them, and beat them ſmall, and then put in your chopped capon and beate them together verie ſmall: then a quart of Creame and the whites of ten Egs, &amp; the crum of a fine Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet, and your ſtuffe, and mingle them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then ſtrain them, and when it is ſtrained put in a good quantitie of Sugar, and a little ſalt. Then take a faire pot, and put your ſtuffe in it, and ſet it to the fire, ſtirre it, and boyle it as thicke as an Apple moiſe, when you haue boyled it, lay it in a fair platter til it be colde: then ſtrain it againe with a litle Roſewater, and when you ſerue it in, caſt ſugar vpon it, &amp; diſh it in thrée partes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Blaminger without Creame or Egs.</head>
                  <p>TAke a capon and almonds, and beat them as before is ſaid: Then take faire hot wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and put into your capon and Almondes: then put the crumme of a Manchet in it, and let it ſtand and ſoke, then ſtrain it, and when it is ſtrayned put in your ſugar, and boyle it of the thicknes of an apple moiſe: then let it cool and ſtraine it againe with a little Roſewater and ſo ſerue it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Stewed meates.</head>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:22136:13"/>
                  <head>To make ſtewed broth either for fleſh or fiſh.</head>
                  <p>TAke halfe a handfull of Roſemarie, and aſmuch of Time, and binde it on a bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with thréed after it is waſht, and put it in the pot, after that the pot is cleane ſcummed, and let it boile a while, then cut ſops of white bread, and put them in a greate charger, and put on the ſame ſcalding broth, &amp; when it is ſoken enough, ſtraine it through a ſtrainer, with a quantitie of wine or good ale, ſo that it be not too tart, and when it is ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, poure it in a pot, and then put in your rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins and Prunes, and ſo let them boyle till the meate be enough. If the broth bee too ſweete put in the more wine, or elſe a litle Vinegre.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſtewed ſteakes.</head>
                  <p>TAke a breſt of Mutton, cutte it in péeces, waſh it clean: then put it in a faire pot: and fill your pot with ale or halfe wine and halfe water, make it ſéeth and ſcum it cleane. Then put into your pot a fagot of Time and Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie, and Parſlie, and thrée or foure Onions cut rounde, take a litle Parſley picked very ſmall, let them boyle altogether. Then take Prunes, ſmal Raiſons, and great Dates, and let them boile altogether: then ſeaſon your
<pb facs="tcp:22136:14"/>pot with theſe ſpices. Take Salt and a litle Saffron Cloues and Mace, Sinamon, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, &amp; a litle Sugar: take a quantitie of theſs ſpices, and put them into your pot, &amp; let them ſtew altogether, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be tender, put a litle Vergious to them, and let them ſtew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, then lay ſoppes of a Manchet vnder them in a platter, at the firſt yee muſt put a good deale of marrow in it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſtew a capon in white broth.</head>
                  <p>TAke marrow bones with the capon, and ſéeth them in faire water, put to it a few maces, and thrée races of Ginger min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and ſalt: and when the Capon is almoſt ſodden, put in a good quantitie of Lettuce, and let them ſéeth a while. Then ſerue in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vpon ſops, and the hearbs vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſtew a Capon in Lemmons.</head>
                  <p>TAke and ſlice your Lemmons, &amp; put them in a platter, and put to them white wine, Roſe water, and Sugar, and ſo boyle them and ſugar till they be tender. Then take the beſt of the broth wherein your Capon is boyled: and put thereto whole mace, whole Pepper, and red Corrans, Barberies, a litle Time and good ſtore of Marrowe. Let them boyle well together, till the broth bee almoſt boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led away, that you haue no more than will
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22136:14"/>wet your ſoppes. Then pour your Lemmons vpon your Capon, and ſeaſon your broth with Vergious and Sugar, and put it alſo vpon your Capon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſtew Chickens.</head>
                  <p>TAke the beſt of your mutton broth, and put thereto a litle whole pepper, and a litle whole Mace, Parſley, and Time, and boyle them. Then put in halfe a diſh of ſwéet butter. Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and a péece of Sugar. Then take a good quantity of Gooſeberies, and boil them, by themſelues in a litle broth, and poure them vpon your Chickens: put into your broth a ſpoonfull of yeſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſtew birdes.</head>
                  <p>TAke ſmall birds faire picked, drawne, the legs cut off, frye them in butter or ſuet wel. Then lay them in a faire cloth and let the Butter ſoak all away: then take Onions minſed ſmall, caſt them in a pot, and take a portion of Sauell, &amp; of wine, draw them through a ſtrainer, and caſt it into the pot, with the Onions and birds fryed, with Cloues, Mace, and a litle Pepper, let all theſe boyle together till it be enough, and put to it ſugar, powder of Ginger, ſalt and Saffron, and ſo ſerue it foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſtew Larks or Sparrowes.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22136:15"/>
                  <p>TAke of your mutton broth the beſt, and put it in a pipkin, and put to it a litle whole Mace, whole pepper, Claret wine, marigolde leaues, Barberies, Roſewater, vergious, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and Marrow, or elſe ſwéet butter: per boil the Larkes before, and then boyle them in the ſame broth, and lay them vpon ſops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>An other way to ſtew Larkes.</head>
                  <p>YOu muſt take them &amp; draw them clean and cut of their féet, &amp; then take a good deal of wine in a platter, and take a good deale of marrow, and put it in the wine, and ſet them on a Chafingdiſh, and let them ſtew there a good while: then take a quantity of ſmall Raiſins and waſh them cleane, and put them into the broth, and take a litle Suger and Synamon, and a few crums of Manchet bread and put them into the Larkes, and let them ſtew altogether. Then take and cut half a dozen toſtes, and lay them in a platter, then put them into a diſh with broth and ſerue them out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to ſtew a mallard.</head>
                  <p>TAke your mallard and ſéeth him in fayre water with a good marrowe bone, and in Cabbage worth, or Cabbage Lettice, or both, and ſome parſnep roots, and Carret roots, and when all theſe bée well ſodden, put in prunes,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22136:15"/>put in prunes enough, and thrée dates, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon him with ſalt, cloues, and Mace, and a litle ſugar, and pepper, and then ſerue it out wyth ſippets, and put the Marie vpon them, and the whole Mace ſay on the ſippets, and the dates quartered, and the prunes, and the roots cut in round ſlices, and lay them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſippets alſo, and the Cabage leaues lay vpon the mallard.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſtew a Cocke.</head>
                  <p>YOu muſt cut him in ſix péeces, and waſh him clean, and take prunes, currans and dates cut very ſmall, and raiſons of the ſun, and ſugar beaten verie ſmall, ſinamon, Ginger, and nutmegs like wiſe beaten, and a litle maidens haire cut verie ſmall, and you muſt put him in a pipkin, and put in almoſt a pint of Muſkadel, and then put your ſpice and ſugar vpon your Cocke, and put in your fruit betwéen euery quarter, and a péece of golde be betwéen euery peece of your Cocke, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you muſt make a lid of wood fit for your pipkin, and cloſe it as cloſe as you can with paſte, that no ayre come out, nor water can come in, and then you muſt fil two braſſe pots ful of water, and ſet on the fire, and make faſt the pipkin in one of the braſſe pots, ſo that the pipkins féet touche not the braſſe pots bottom, nor the pot ſides and ſo let them boils four and twenty houres, and fil
<pb facs="tcp:22136:16"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:22136:16"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22136:17"/>vp the pot ſtill as it boiles away, with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pot that ſtands by, and when it is boyled, take out your gold, and let him drink it faſting and it ſhall help him: this is approued.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to ſtew a Neates foote.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt let your Neates foote be ſcalded and made cleane. Then take Onions, ſlic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them and boile them well in faire water</p>
                  <p>Then take half water and halfe wine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> muche as neede to serue for the boyling of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Neates foot, which wil be ſoone enough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it in a pipkin. Put therein ſome cloues, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the whole pepper, and take the onions out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> water they were sodden in, &amp; put them int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the ſame pipkin, &amp; the neats <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eet with them ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it be almoſt enough. Then take a litle Vergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, half a diſh of ſweet butter, and a litle ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and let them boyle a litle together, &amp; ſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> them in vpon sops.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make ſtewed pottage in L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</head>
                  <p>TAke a faire pot, and fil it full of water, take a ſaueer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul of Oyle Oliue, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it into the pot<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet your pot on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and let it boyl. Then take parslie rootes, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fennel roots, and scrape them cleane, then tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them of the bigneſſe of a Prune, and put them into the pot. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take bread, and cut it in ſop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and caſt it into a pot of wine: the wine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:22136:17"/>put it in the pot. Then take roſemary, Time. and parſley and binde them together, and put them into the pot: then take Dates, Prunes, Corrans and great Raiſons, and waſh them cleane, and put them in the pot. Then ſeaſon your pot with ſalt, Cloues, Mace, and a litle ſugar. If it be not red enough, take Saunders and colour your pot therwith, looke that your broth be thick enough.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to ſtew beefe.</head>
                  <p>TAke béefe and ſmyte it in péeces, and waſhe it in faire water, and ſtrain that water and put it in the potte with the Béefe, and boyle them together. Then take Pepper, Cloues, Mace, Onions, parſley and ſage, caſt it therto and let it boile together: Then make liquor with bread and thicke it: and ſo let if ſéethe a good while after that the thicking is in. Then put in Saffron, ſalt, and vinegar, and ſo ſerue it foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another way to ſtew Beefe.</head>
                  <p>BOil your flank of béef verie tender, til the broth bée almoſt conſumed, then put the broth into a pipkin, &amp; put to it Onions, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret roots ſheed ſmal, being render ſodden before and pepper groſe beaten, vergious; and halfe a diſh of ſwéet butter, and ſo lay it vpon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make brine to keepe Lard.</head>
                  <p>TAke faire Water and white ſalte, and all
<pb facs="tcp:22136:18"/>to ſtirre them with a ſtaffe a good prity while: then lay the lard in it one night and one day to ſoake out the blood of the Lard. Then make new brine in like maner, and beat it, vntil the time that the ſalt is conſumed, and then it will be clear: that done, put the brine in a prety tub that hath a couer wel faſtened, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay in your Lard, and kéep it vnder brine with ſplints, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> couer the tub cloſe: and thus ye may kéepe the Lard white and ſwéet two or thrée yeres, with change of Brine when néed ſhal require.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Maunger Blaunch.</head>
                  <p>TAke half a pound of Rice verie clean picked and waſhed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beat it very fine, and ſearſe it through a fine ſearſe, &amp; put the fineſt of it in a quart of mornings milke, &amp; ſtrain it through a ſtrainer, and put it in a faire pot, and ſet it on the fire, but it muſt be but a ſoft fire, &amp; ſtill ſtir it with a broad ſtick. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is a litle thick take it from the fire, and take the brawne of a verie tender Capon, and pul it in as ſmal pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as ye can, and the Capon muſt be ſodden in faire water, &amp; the brawn of it muſt bee pulled as ſmall as a horſe haire with your fingers, &amp; put it into the milke which is but halfe thicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and then put in as much ſugar, as ye think wil make it ſwéet, and put in a dozen ſpoonfuls of good Roſewater, and ſet it to the fire again
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22136:18"/>and ſtir it well, &amp; in the ſtirring, all to beate if with your ſtick, from the one ſide of the pan to the other, and when it is as thick as pap, take it from the fire, and put it in a fair platter, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is cold, lay thrée ſlices in a diſh, and caſt a litle ſugar on it, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to ſowce a Pigge.</head>
                  <p>YOu muſt take white wine, &amp; a litle ſwéet broth, and halfe a ſcore of nutmegs cut in quarters: then take ſwéete Margeram, roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, baies, and Time, and let them boile all together, ſcum them very cleane: &amp; when they be boiled, put them in an earthen pan, and the ſirrop alſo, and when ye ſerue them, a quarter in a diſh, and the baies &amp; nutmegs on the top.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Baked meates.</head>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make paſte, and to raiſe coffins.</head>
                  <p>TAke fine flower, and lay it on a boord, &amp; take a certaine of yolkes of Egges as your quantitie of flower is, then take a certaine of Butter and water, and botle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together, but you muſt take héed ye put not too many yolks of Egges, for if you doe it will make it dry and not pleaſant in eating: and ye muſt take béed ye put not in too much Butter, for if you doe, it wil make it ſo fine and ſo ſhort that you cannot raiſe: and this paſte is good to
<pb facs="tcp:22136:19"/>raiſe all maner of Coffins: like wiſe if ye bake Veniſon, bake it in the paſte aboue named.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fine paſte another way.</head>
                  <p>TAke butter and ale, and ſeeth them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: then take your flower, and put there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into three egs, ſugar, ſaffron, and ſalt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſhort paſte in Lent.</head>
                  <p>TAke thick almond milke ſéething hot, &amp; ſo wet your flower with it: &amp; ſallet oyle fried, &amp; ſaffron, and ſo miggle your paſte altogether, and that will make good paſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake Veniſon, or mutton in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Veniſon.</head>
                  <p>TAke leane veniſon or mutton, and take out all the ſinewes, then chop your fleſh veris ſmal, and ſeaſon it with a litle pepper and ſalt and beaten cloues, and a good handful of Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>l ſeeds, and mingle them altogether: Then take your Larde, and cut it of the bigneſſe of a gooſe quill, and the length of your finger, and put it in a diſh of vineger, &amp; al to waſh it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: then take meale as it dooth come from the mil, and make paſte with colde water, and ſée that it be very ſtiff then take a ſhéet, and make a laying of the minced fleſh vpon the ſhéet, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bredth that your Lard is of length, then make a laying of your Lard vpon your fleſh, and let your larde bee one from another, the breadth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22136:19"/>of one of the peeces of the Larde, and ſo make foure layings of lard, and thrée layings of fleſh one vpon another, ſo preſſe it downe with your hands as hard as you can for breaking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſte and caſt in a handfull of pepper and ſalt, &amp; bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten cloues, ſo cloſe vp your paſſe, &amp; let it bake two houres.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make ſweet pies of Veale.</head>
                  <p>TAke veale and perboile if very tender, then chop it ſmall, then take twiſe as much béefe ſuet, and chop it ſmall, then mince both them together, then put currans and minced Dates to them, then ſeaſon your fleſh after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Take Pepper, ſalt, and Saffron, Cloues, Mace, ſinamon, Ginger and Sugar, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon your fleſh with each of theſe a quantitye, and mingle them altogether. This doone take fine flower, butter, egs, and Saffron, &amp; make your paſte withall as fine as you can, &amp; make your pie with it, and when it is made, fill it with your ſtuffe. Then put vppon your pye, Prunes, Corans, Dates, a little ſugar, and yolkes of egs hard. Then couer your pie and ſet it on a paper, and ſet it in the Ouen, and let it bake ſokingly, if it be ſcortcht aboue lay a paper double on it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Chewets of Veale.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22136:20"/>
                  <p>TAke a leg of beale and perboyl it, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mince it with beefe ſuet, take almoſt as much of your ſuet as of your veale, and take a good quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Ginger, &amp; a litle ſaffron to colour it: take halfe a goblet of white wine, and two or three good handfull of grapes, and put them all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſalt, and ſo put them in Coffins, and let them boyle a quarter of an houre.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make chewets another way.</head>
                  <p>TAke a litle Veale and ſlice it, and perboile it, then take it vp &amp; preſſe it in a faire cloth, and mince it very fine, take Corans and dates and cut them very ſmall, take ſome marie or ſuet, and the yolkes of three or foure Egges, and pepper, ſalt, and mace fine beaten, and the crums of bread fine grated: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mingle al theſe together, and put in ſuet enough, and they wil be good pies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Chewets in Lent.</head>
                  <p>TAke a freſh Eele and flea it, and cut of the fiſh from the bone, mince it ſmal and pare two or thrée wardens and mince the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> likewiſe ſmall, as much of them as of the Eele or Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and temper them together, and ſeaſon it with Ginger, Pepper, cloues, Mace and ſalte, and a little colour it with Saunders, and put currans and prunes, and minced great raiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and Dates, as you do to the other pies of fleſh,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22136:20"/>when it is halfe baked put them out, and put to it a litle vergious: and if your Gelly be not fat put to it a little Sallet Oyle fried with ſome ſweet flowers or hearbes, if yee put a lyttle Roſewater and ſalt it is good, but if you haue any fat of fiſh it is better then oyle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Oyſter chewets.</head>
                  <p>TAke a peck of oyſters, &amp; waſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clean. Then ſhel them, and waſh them in a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender fair and clean, then ſeeth them in faire water a litle, and when they bee ſodden, ſtraine the water from them, &amp; cut them ſmall as pie meat, ſeaſon them with a little pepper, a peniworth of cloues and mace, a peniworth of ſinamon and ginger, a peniworth of Sugar, a little ſaffron and ſalt: then take a handful of Corans, ſixe dates minced ſmall, and mingle them altogether: then make your paſte with a quantitie of fine flower, ten yolks of Egges, a quantitie of butter, with a little Saffron and boyled water, then raiſe vp your chewets, and put in the bottom of your chewets a little but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and caſt vpon them Prunes, Dates, and currans, ſo cloſe them and bake them: let not your Ouen be too hot, for they would haue but little baking, then draw them, and put in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of them two ſpoonfuls of vergious and but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſo ſerue them in &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22136:21"/>
                  <head>How to make ſpeciall good pies either of mutton or Veale.</head>
                  <p>LEt your meat bee perboiled, and mince it very fine, and then your ſuet by it ſelf: and after put to the meate, and mince them well together, then put thereto fiue or ſixe yolks of egs being hard ſodden and minced, ſmal Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, Dates fine minced: ſeaſon it with Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Ginger, Cloues and Mace, a handfull of carowayes, ſugar, and vergious, and ſome ſalt and a litle pepper, and ſo put it into your paſſe, whether they be chewets or Trunk pies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make paſte, and to bake chickens.</head>
                  <p>TAke water, and put in a good peece of but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let it ſéeth as hot as you can blowe off your Butter into your flower, and breake two yolks of Egges, and one white, and put in a good peece of Sugar, and colour your paſte with Saffron, then ſhal it be ſhort Then take your chickens, and ſeaſon them with Pepper, ſalt, Saffron, and great Raiſons, cloues, mace Corans, Prunes, and Dates, then cloſe them vp, &amp; make a little hole in the midſt of the lid. Then ſet it in the Ouen, and to make ſirrop for the ſame pie, take Malmſey, Creame, and two yolkes of Egges, and beate them togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22136:21"/>and put in Synamon and Sugar, and when the pie is almoſt baked, then put in the ſirrop, and let them bake together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake chickins in Summer.</head>
                  <p>CVt off their feete, truſſe them in the cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fins. Then take for euerie Chicken a good handfull of Gooſeberries, and put into the pie with the Chickens. Then take a good quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of butter, and put about euerie chicken in the pie. Then take a good quantitie of Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and ginger, and put it in the pie with ſalt and let them bake an houre, when they be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, take for euerie pie the yolke of an eg, and halfe a goblet full of vergious and a good qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſugar, and put them altogether into the pie to the chickens, and ſo ſerue them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake chickens in winter.</head>
                  <p>CVt of their feete, and truſſe them, and put them in the pies, take to euerie pie a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Corrans or Prunes, and put them in the pie with the Chickens. Then take a good quantity of Butter to euerie chicken, and put in the pie: then take a good quantity of ginger, and ſalt and ſeaſon them together, &amp; put them in the pie, let it bake the ſpace of an houre &amp; a half, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be baken, take ſauce as is afore ſaid, and ſo ſerue them in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake Chickens with Damſons.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22136:22"/>
                  <p>TAke your Chickens, draw them and waſh them, then breake their bones and lay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a platter, then take foure handfulles of fine flower, and lay it on a faire boord, put thereto twelue yolks of Egs, a diſh of butter, and a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſaffron: mingle them altogether, and make your paſte therewith. Then make ſixe coffins, and put in euery coffin a lumpe of butter of the bigneſſe of a walnut: then ſeaſon your ſixe cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fins with one ſpooneful of cloues &amp; Mace, two ſpoonefuls of ſinamon, and one of Sugar, and a ſpoonefull of ſalt. Then put your Chickins into your pies: then take Damſons and pare away the outward peel of them, and put twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in euery of your pies, round about your chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put into euery of your coffins, a ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Currans. Then cloſe them vp, and put them into the Ouen, and let them bee there three quarters of an houre.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake a Turkie.</head>
                  <p>TAke and cleane your Turkie on the backe, and bruiſe all the bones: then ſeaſon it with ſalt, and pepper groſſe beaten, and put into it good ſtore of butter: he muſt haue fiue howers baking.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake a Feſant.</head>
                  <p>TRuſſe him like a hen, and perboil him, then ſet him with cloues, then take a litle vergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22136:22"/>and ſaffron, and colour it with a feather, then take ſalt, Mace and Ginger to ſeaſon it, and ſo put it in the paſte, and bake it till it be half enough. Then put in a litle vergious and the yolke of an eg beaten together: then bake it till it be enough.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake a Capon inſteed of a Feaſant.</head>
                  <p>CVt off his legs and his wings, &amp; after the maner of a Feaſant truſſe him ſhort, then perboile him a litle, and Larde him with ſweet lard: ſo put him into the coffin, and take a litle pepper and ſalt and caſt about him. And take a good halfe diſh of butter &amp; put into the coffin, ſo let him bake the ſpace of foure houres and ſerue it forth cold in ſteed of a Feaſant. So likewiſe bake a Feaſant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake Red Deare.</head>
                  <p>YOu muſt take a handful of fennel, a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of winter ſauorie, a handfull of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie, a handful of Time, and a handful of Baie leaues, and when your liquour ſéeths that you perboile your veniſon in, put in your hearbs alſo, and perboile your veniſon til it be half enough, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take it out, &amp; lay it vpon a fair boord that the water may run fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, then take a knife and prick it ful of holes, and while it is warm, haue a faire tray with vineger ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ſo put your veniſon therein from mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:22136:23"/>vntil night, and euer now and then turn it vpſide downe, &amp; then at night haue your cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin readie, and this done, ſeaſon it with Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Nutmegs and Ginger, Pepper and ſalt, and when you haue ſeaſoned it, put it into your coffin, and put a good quantity of ſwéete But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into it, &amp; then put it into the Ouen at night when you go to bed, and in the morning draw it forth, and put in a ſawcer ful of Vinegar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your pie at a hole aboue in the top of it, ſo that the vinegar may run into euerie place of it, and then ſtop the hole againe, and turne the bottome vpward, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake Veniſon.</head>
                  <p>PErboile your Veniſon, then ſeaſon it with Pepper and ſalt, ſome what groſe beaten, and a litle Ginger, and good ſtore of ſwéete butter. And when the Veniſon is tender ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: put to it halfe a dozen ſpoonfuls of Claret Wine, and ſhake it well together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake a Crane or a buſtard.</head>
                  <p>PErboile him a litle, then Larde him with ſwéet lard, and put him in the coffin. Take Pepper and ſalt, a good quantity, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon them together and caſt vpon it. Then take Butter, and put in the coffin, let it bane thrée houres.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake a Mallard.</head>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:22136:23"/>
                  <p>FIrſt truſſe them, and perboile them, and put them into the coffin: then ſeaſon them with pepper and ſalt, and four or fiue Onions péeled and ſliced, and put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> altogether, with a good péece of ſwéet butter vnto the Mallard and ſo let them bake two houres, &amp; when they be baked, put in halfe a goblet of Vergious for euerie Mallard, and ſo ſerue them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake a wilde boare.</head>
                  <p>TAke thrée partes of water, &amp; the fourth part of white wine, and put thereto ſalt aſmuch as ſhal ſeaſon it, &amp; let it boile ſo til it be almoſt enough: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take it out of the broth and let it lie til it be through colde: Then Lard it, and lay it in courſe paſte, in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, and then ſeaſon it with pepper, ſalt, and ginger, &amp; put in twiſe ſo much ginger as pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. And when it is half baked, fil your paſties with white wine, and all to ſhake the paſtie, &amp; ſo put it into the Ouen again, til it be enough: Then let it ſtand fiue or ſix daies, or euer that you eat of them, and that time it will be very good meate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake wilde Duckes.</head>
                  <p>DReſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faire, &amp; perboil the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then ſeaſon them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pepper &amp; ſalt, a few whole cloues amongſt them, and Onions ſmal minced, and ſwéete butter, Vergious, and a litle Sugar.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22136:24"/>
                  <head>To bake calues feete.</head>
                  <p>TAke Calues féet and ſéeth them tender, pul off the haire, then ſlit them, and make your paſte fine, &amp; when you haue made your coffin, before you put in your féet, take good Raiſons and mince them ſmal, and plucke out the ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, and ſtrewe them in the bottome of your pie: then ſeaſon your féete with Pepper, ſalt, cloues and mace, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay in the féet, and ſtrew currons on them, and Sugar and a good péece of butter in it, and cloſe it vp, and make a litle hole in the lid, and when it is almoſt baked e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, put in a meſſe of Vergious, and ſo ſerue them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake Calues feete after the French faſhion.</head>
                  <p>TAke the féet, pul off al the haire, and make them cleane, and boile them a litle til they be ſomwhat tender, then make your paſte, and ſeaſon your calues féet with pepper, ſalt and Sinamon, and put them in your paſte, with a quantity of ſwéet Butter, Parſlie and Ony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among them, ſo cloſe it vp, and ſet it into the Ouen till they be halfe baken. Then take them foorth, and open the crowne, and put in more butter &amp; ſome Vineger, ſo let them ſtand in the Ouen til they be throughly baked.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For to bake a Pigge.</head>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:22136:24"/>
                  <p>FLea your Pigge, and take our all that is within his bellie clean, &amp; waſh him well, and after perboile him, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeaſon it with Pepper, Salt, Nutmegs, Mace and cloues, and ſo lay him with good ſtore of butter in the paſte: Then ſet it in the Ouen till it be baked enough.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake a Pig like a Fawne.</head>
                  <p>TAke him when he is in the haire, and flea him the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeaſon it with pepper &amp; ſalt, cloues and Mace: then take claret wine, Vergious, Roſewater, ſugar, Sinamon, and ginger, and boyle them altogether: then lay your Pigge flat like a Fawne or a Kid, and put your Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop vnto it, with a litle ſwéet Butter, and ſo bake it leyſurely.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake a Neats tong.</head>
                  <p>SEeth the tong halfe enough, and blanch it and cut it in two, then ſcorch it, and ſeaſon it with pepper and ſalt, and put it in a coffin and a good quantity of Marrow with it, and when it is almoſt baken, put in ſome red wine and ſugar.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake an Hare.</head>
                  <p>TAke your hare and perboil him, and mince him, and then beat him in a morter very fine liuer and al, if you will, and ſeaſon it with all kind of ſpices and ſalt, and doe him together
<pb facs="tcp:22136:25"/>with the yolkes of ſeauen or eight egges, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye haue made him vp together, draw lard verie thick through him, and mingle them all togither, and put him in a pie, and put in butter before ye cloſe him vp.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>For to bake a Gammon of Bacon.</head>
                  <p>BOile your gammon of Bacon, and ſtuffe it with parſley and ſage, and yolkes of hard egs and when it is boiled, ſtuffe it and let it boyle againe, ſeaſon it with Pepper, Cloues and mace, ſticke whole Cloues faſt in it: Then lay it ſo in your paſte with ſalt butter, and ſo bake it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a rare conceite, with Veale baked.</head>
                  <p>TAke veale and ſmite it in litle péeces, and ſéeth it in faire water, then take parſley, Sage, Iſop and Sauorie, and ſhred them ſmall, and put them in the pot when it boileth. Take powder of Pepper, canel, mace, ſaffron and ſalt, and let all theſe boyle together till it be enough. Then take vp the fleſhe from the broth, and let the broth coole, when it is colde, take the yolks of egges with the whites, and ſtraine them, and put them into the broth, ſo manie til the broth be ſtiffe enough, then make faire coffins, and couch thrée péeces or foure in one coffin of the Veale: and take Dates min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:22136:25"/>and prunes, powder of pepper, Ginger and vergious, and put it to the broth. Then put the liquor in the coffins, like as ye do with a cuſtard, and bake it till it be enough, and ſo ſerue it foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a florentine.</head>
                  <p>TAke Veale, &amp; ſome of the Kidney of the loyne, or cold Veale roaſted, cold capon or feaſant, which of them you will, and minſe it verie ſmal, with ſwéet Suet, put vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it two or thrée yolkes of Egges, being hard ſodde, Corans and Dates ſmal ſhred. Seaſon it with a litle Sinamon and ginger a very li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Cloues and Mace, with a litle ſalt and ſugar, and a litle Time finely ſhred. Make your paſte fine with butter and yolks of egs, and ſugar, rolle it very thin, and ſo lay it in a platter with butter vnderneath, and ſo cut your couer and lay it vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a pie to keep long.</head>
                  <p>YOu muſt firſt perboile your fleſh &amp; preſſe it, &amp; when it is preſſed, ſeaſon it with pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ſalt whileſt it is hot, then lard it, make your paſte of rie flower, it muſt be very thick, or elſe it wil not holde, when it is ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; larded, lay it in your pie, then caſt on it before you cloſe it, a good deale of cloues and Mace beaten ſmall, and lay vpon that a good
<pb facs="tcp:22136:26"/>deale of Butter, and ſo cloſe it vp: but you muſt leaue a hole in the top of the lid, &amp; when it hath ſtood two houres in the Ouen, you muſt fill it as full of vinigar as you can, and then ſtop the hole as cloſe as you can with paſte, and then ſet it into the Ouen again: your Ouen muſt bée verie hot at the firſt, and then your pies will keep a great while: the longer you kéep them the better wil they be: and when ye haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them out of the ouen, and that they be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt cold, you muſt ſhake them betwéene your hands, and ſet them with the bottom vpward, and when you ſet them into the Ouen, be well ware that one pie touch not another by more than ones hand bredth: Remember alſo to let them ſtand in the Ouen after the Vinegar be in, two houres and more.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake ſmall meats.</head>
                  <p>TAke Egges and ſeeth them hard, then take the yolkes out of them and braie them in a Morter, and temper them with Creame, and then ſtrain them, &amp; put to them pepper, ſaffron cloues, mace, ſmal raiſons, almonds blanched &amp; ſmal ſhred, &amp; grated bread: take Peares alſo ſodden in ale, &amp; bray &amp; ſtrain the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> liquor, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t therto baſtard and honey, &amp; put it in a pan and ſtirre it on the fire till it be we ſodden. Then make litle coffins and ſet the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:22136:26"/>in the Ouen vntil they bee hard, and then you muſt take them out again, and put the foreſaid liquor into them, and ſo ſerue them foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a pie in Lent.</head>
                  <p>TAke Eeles and flea them, and cut them from the bone, take Wardens and Figs, &amp; mince them together, and put to them Cloues and mace, pepper, ſalt, and Saffron, and ſeaſon al theſe together, and mingle it with great and ſmall Raiſons, Prunes and Dates, cut it in ſmall peeces, and ſo put it into the coffin, and let it bake halfe an houre.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a Cuſtard in Lent.</head>
                  <p>TAke halfe a pound of almonds, blanch them and beate them in a morter. Then take a quart of fair water, warm it luke warme, and ſtrayne your liquour with the almonds. Then take a peece of the ſpawn of a Pike, of a Carp or a Roch, and beat it in a morter, then ſtraine it into your almonds: for lacke of ſpawne yee may take two ſpoonfuls of the flower of Rice, and put it into your almonds Then take Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, cloues, Maces, Saffron and ſalt, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon your liquor therwith, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ye would ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a cuſtard of creame, then take three hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of fine flower, and almoſt a pint of fair wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter boyling hot, and a litle Saffron, and make your paſte therwith. Then make your cuſtard
<pb facs="tcp:22136:27"/>and when it is made, put ſmall Raiſons an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dates in the bottome of your Cuſtarde, as you do vnto a cuſtard of creame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake Oyſters ſhels and all.</head>
                  <p>TAke the beſt Oyſters faire ſhaled, and the faireſt &amp; ſmootheſt ſhels, waſh a good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and to make them ſmooth, rub one ſhel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, and when they are very clean make your pie: and then let your grauie run through a ſtrayner of your Oyſters and waſh your oyſters very clean, and ſeaſon them with Pepper and ſalt. Then take out of the deepeſt ſhelles, and put into them thrée Oyſters and thrée cloues, and a litle peece of butter, and lay a flat ſhell vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, and thus ſet your pie with the ſhels and the Oyſters in them till they be full, and in voyde places put in a péece of But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: then cloſe your pie, and ſet it into the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and when it hath ſtood there half an hour draw your pie, and then put in a ſawcer full of your grauie. Then put the pie into the Ouen againe, and ſo let it ſtand one other halfe how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and then ſerue it forth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake Peares, quinces, and wardens.</head>
                  <p>YOu muſt take and pare them, and then coare them: then make your paſte with faire water and Butter, and the yolke of an Egge, and ſette your Orenges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22136:27"/>to the paſte, and then bake it well: Then fill your paſte almoſt ful with Sinamon, Ginger and Sugar: alſo apples muſt be taken after the ſame ſort, ſauing that whereas the core ſhould be cut out they muſt be filled with but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter euerie one: the hardeſt apples are beſt, and likewiſe are Peares and wardens, and none of them all but the Wardens may be perboi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and the ouen muſt be of a temperate heat, two houres to ſtand is enough.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake quince pies.</head>
                  <p>PAre them and take out all the Core: then perboyle them in water till they bée ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: Then take them foorth: and let the water runne from them till they be drie. Then put into euerie Quince, Sugar, ſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and ginger, and fill euerie pie therewith, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you may let them bake the ſpace of an houre, and ſo ſerue them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake orenges.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt take twelue Orenges, and pare away the yellow rinde of them, cut them in two péeces, and wring out the iuyce of them, then lay your pilles in faire water, and when it is boyling hot, put your Orenges therin, let them ſeeth therein vntill the water be bitter. Then haue another potte of water readie vppon the fyre, and when it dooth ſéethe, put your O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renge
<pb facs="tcp:22136:28"/>pils therein, and let them ſeeth again in the ſame water vntil they be very tender: then take your Orenges out of the pot, &amp; put them in a baſon of fayre cold water, and with your thombe take out the core of your Orenges and waſh them cleane in the ſame water, and lay them in a faire platter, ſo that the water may run from them: then take a quart of Baſtard, clearet wine, or white wine, if you take a quart of Baſtard, put thereto a quartern of ſugar: if you take claret or white wine, ye muſt take to euerie pint a quarterne of Sugar, and ſet it to the fire in a faire pot: then put your Orenges therein, and ſeeth them till the liquor come to a ſirrop: when it is come to a ſirrop, take a fair earthen pot, and put your Orenges and your ſirrop altogether, ſo that your Orrenges may be couered with your ſirrop, if you lacke ſyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop, you muſt take a pinte of Claret wine, and a quarterne of Sugar, and make thereof a ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop, and put it into your Orenges, and ſtoppe your pot cloſe, after this maner you may keep them two moneths, and when you will bake them, take an ounce of Synamon, and half an ounce of ginger, and beat them ſmal, then take two pound of ſugar, and beat it in like maner. Then put your ſugar, Sinamon and Ginger in a faire platter, and mingle them together.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22136:28"/>Then take foure handful of fine flower, &amp; lay it vpon a faire board, and make an hole in the midſt of the flower with your hand: then take a pinte of fair water, &amp; eight ſpoonfuls of Oyl, and a little ſaffron, and let them ſeeth altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and when it ſeeths put it in the hole in the midſt of the flower, and knead your paſte ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with then make little round coffins of the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of an orenge, and when they be made, put a little ſugar in the bottom of them: then take your Orenge pilles and fill them full of ſugar and ſpices afore rehearſed, and put them into your coffins, and fill the coffins ful of the ſame ſugar and ſpices: when the ſpices be in them, cloſe them vp, and ſet them vppon papers, and bake them in an ouen or baking pan but your Ouen may not be too hot if your coffins be dry after the baking, you may make a litle hole with the point of a knife vpon the couer of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and with a poone put a little of the ſirrop to them, at another ſeaſon you muſt make your paſte with foure handfuls of fine flower, and twelue yolks of egs, and a litle ſaffron, make your paſte therewith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another good way to bake Orenges.</head>
                  <p>PAre the vtter rinde as thin as you can: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take the Orenges, and cut out a litle hole in the top, &amp; with a narrow pointed knife
<pb facs="tcp:22136:29"/>picke out as nigh as yée can al the pames: then ſeeth them in faire water boyling a ſoft pace: and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the water is bitter haue more water readye, and change the firſt water, and ſo let them ſéeth in the ſecond water a good while ſoft<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly boyling, let them not be very tender, for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that boyling ye muſt put them in an other liquor that muſt be water and hony very ſwéet ſodden together &amp; ſcummed: then put into that a good quantity of Saffron, and ſo put in your orenges, and let them ſéeth well in that water, til they be verie tender, if yee will bake them, put Claret wine and ſugar together, and let it boyle wel. Then fil your Orenges of drie Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and Ginger, and turne the hole of your O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renges vp ward: then put the Claret wine in, till your coffin be almoſt full: and ſée that there be Sugar enough in the coffin and cloſe it vp, and a litle before ye wil ſerue it in, put in more of the Claret wine and Sugar that was firſte ſodden, at the hole aboue in the coffin Thus ye may keepe your Orenges in that ſame liquor that ye did ſéeth them in firſt, a moneth or more and if ye think that the liquor changeth: ſéeth it againe and it wil amend, and if you think that the Orenges doo not looke yellow enough, put Saffron in the liquor, and with a feather col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour your Orenges.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:22136:29"/>
                  <head>To bake Peaches.</head>
                  <p>TAke Peaches, pare them, and cut them in two péeces, &amp; take out the ſtones as cleane as you can for breaching of the Peach: then make your pie thrée ſquare to bake fowre in a pie, let your paſte be verie fine, then make your dredge with fine Sugar, Synamon and Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: and firſt lay a little dredge in the bottome of your pies: Then put in Peaches, and fill vp your coffins with your Dredge, and put into euery coffin thrée ſpoonfuls of Roſewater. Let not your Ouen be too hot. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To bake pippins.</head>
                  <p>TAke your pippins and pare them, and make your coffin of fine paſte, and caſt a little ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar in the bottome of the pie. Then put in your Pippins, and ſet them as cloſe as ye can: then take ſugar, ſinamon, and Ginger, and make them in a dredge, and fill the Pie therewith: ſo cloſe it, and let it bake two houres but the Ouen muſt not be too hot.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a good Caſtard.</head>
                  <p>TAke a platter full of Creame, if it bee a quart, then take ſixe yolks of Egges, to a pint thrée Egges, and when you ſet your Creame, ouer the fire, cut your butter in ſmal peeces and but it into your creame, &amp; it be litle more then the quantitie of a Walnut it is
<pb facs="tcp:22136:30"/>enough, and ſeaſon it with ſalt, Sugar, cloues, mace, and ſaffron, and ſo couer it, and let it be ſet vpon a chafingdiſh or pot of ſéething water, and when it is well hardned, caſt on it minced Dates and ſmall Raiſons, and ſo let it boyle till ye think it be wel hardned: and then ſerue them foorth. &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a Cuſtard in Lent.</head>
                  <p>TAke the milt of any maner of freſh fiſh, and a little of the milt of a white Hering, and a quantitie of blanched almonds, and crums of bread, and mingle al theſe together and a litle Water and Sugar, and a quantitie of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, and mingle that together: ſeaſon it as ye would do another cuſtard with al maner of ſpices. Then mingle therwith Raiſons cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, and Dates, cut in peeces, and ſo bake it in a platter or paſte, whether ye will, the ſpace of halfe an houre, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Another way to make a Cuſtard in Lent.</head>
                  <p>TAke blanched almonds and bray them ſmal put crummes of white bread in the braying of the almonds. Then let a Pike be ſodden, or fat Eels, that ye may haue the beſt of the broth and put that in the bottom of your platter, put in alſo minced dates and corrans. Then ſtrain your almonds with the water ſodden with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar. Then ſeaſon it with ſugar, ſaffron, cloues
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:22136:30"/>and Mace: then put in all the ſtuffe in the plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſo boyle it vppon a chafingdiſh a good while: ſée the platter be not couered, for if it be the Cuſtard will neuer waxe harde: when ye ſerue it forth, caſt Sugar on it, &amp; if your dates and corrans be ſodden in the fiſh broth afore ye put them in the platter, they wil be the better, put to a litle ſalt in the making, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a tarte of apples and Orenge pilles.</head>
                  <p>TAke your orenges, and lay them in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a day and a night, then ſeeth them in faire water and hony, and let them ſeeth till they be ſoft: then let them ſoak in the ſirrop a day and a night: then take them forth and cut them ſmall, and then make your tart and ſeaſon your Apples with Sugar, Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and Ginger, and put in a péece of butter, and lay a courſe of Apples, and betweene the ſame courſe of apples, a courſe of Orenges, and ſo courſe by courſe, and ſeaſon your Oren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as you ſeaſoned your Apples, with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more ſugar, then lay on the lid and put it in the ouen, and when it is almoſt baked, take Roſewater and Sugar, and boyle them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther till it be ſomwhat thick, then take out the Tart, and take a feather and ſpread the roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water and Sugar on the lid, and ſet it into the
<pb facs="tcp:22136:31"/>Ouen againe, and let the ſugar harden on the lid, and let it not burne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a tart of Apples.</head>
                  <p>PAre your apples and cut away the core, &amp; cut the remnant in ſmal péeces, &amp; ſéeth it in roſe water or wine til they be ſoft, &amp; ye muſt ſtirre it al the while it ſéeths, then draw it through a ſtrainer, and ſeaſon it with ſugar ſinamon &amp; ginger, &amp; ſpread it in your paſte: &amp; if you wil, ye may ſerue it in a diſh without paſt &amp; cut a date or two &amp; lay it on, for a change yée may collour it with Saunders if you wil.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a good tart of Cheries.</head>
                  <p>TAke your cheries and pick out the ſtones of them: then take raw yolks of egs, and put them into your cheries, then take ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, Sinamon and Ginger, and Cloues, and put to your Cheries &amp; make your Tart with all the Egges, your tart muſt be of an inche high, when it is made put in your cheries wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout any liquor, and caſt Sugar, Sinamon, and ginger, vpon it, and cloſe it vp, lay it on a paper, &amp; put it in the Ouen, when it is half ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken draw it out, and put the liquor that you let of your cheries into the Tart: then take mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten butter, and with a feather anoint your lid therwith. Then take fine beaten Sugar and caſt vpon it: then put your Tarte into the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22136:31"/>again, and let it bake a good while, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is baken draw it foorth, &amp; caſt Sugar &amp; Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water vpon it, and ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a tart of Cheries, when the ſtones be out, another way.</head>
                  <p>SEeth them in white wine or in Claret, and ſtrain them thick: when they be ſodden: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take two yolks of egges &amp; thicken it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: then ſeaſon it with Sinamon, Ginger, and Sugar, and bake it, and ſo ſerue it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a tart of Damſons.</head>
                  <p>SEeth the Damſons in Wine, and ſtraine them with a litle Creame: then boile your ſtuffe ouer the fire til it be thick, put there to ſugar, Sinamon, and Ginger, ſo ſpred them on your paſte, but ſet it not in the Ouen after, but let the paſte be baked before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a tart of Egges.</head>
                  <p>TAke twentie yolks of Egs, and half a pound of butter, and ſtraine them altogether into a plater: then put two good handfuls of ſugar in it, ſixe ſpoonfuls of Roſewater, and ſtirre them altogether. Then make your paſte with twoo handfuls of fine flower, and ſixe yolks of Egs, and a quarter of a diſh of Butter: then make your Tart, and put your ſtuffe therein and lay your Tart vpon a ſheete of Paper, and ſo put it into the Ouen, and when that it is baked
<pb facs="tcp:22136:32"/>enough, then draw it out of the Ouen, and caſt a litle ſugar on it, and ſo ſerue it foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a good tart of Creame.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quart of Creame, and put in twelue yolks of egges, and a litle Saffron, ſtraine them. Then put it in a pot and boile it, but all the time it ſtandeth on the fire it muſt be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a ſticke for burning. Alſo ere ye boil it, ye muſt put a good diſh of butter in it, when it is boiled, put in your Sugar, as muche as wil make it ſwéet: then make your paſte with Butter. Egges, Sugar, with a litle Saffron and fine flower, and make your Tart with it and drie it in the Ouen, and when it is dry, put in a litle Roſewater and butter, then fill your tart with the ſtuffe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſtrained, ſo bake it, and when it is baked, ſprinkle a little Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water and Sugar, and a litle Butter molten vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a tart of Prunes.</head>
                  <p>YOu muſt ſeeth the prunees with Wyne, then ſtraine them, and ſeaſon it with Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, ſo bake it with paſte, and firſt prick it in the bottome if that you wil boile your ſtuffe vpon a chafingdiſh, then the leſſe bàking after ward wil ſerue it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a tart of Spinnage.</head>
                  <p>TAke ſome caſt creame, and ſeeth ſome Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22136:32"/>in faire water till it be very ſoft, then put it into a Collender, that the water may ſoake from it: then ſtraine the ſpinnage, and caſt the creame together, let there bee good plentie of Spinnage: ſet it vpon a chafingdiſh of coales, and put to it Sugar and ſome Butter, and let it boyle a while Then put it in the paſte, and bake it, and caſt blaunche pouder on it, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To mke a tart of Veale.</head>
                  <p>TAke two kidneis of Veale and broyle them, then take off all the ſkin and chop the fat ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſmall, and put two yolks of egs, a handfull of Corrans, ſixe Dates cut ſmall two handfull of ſugar, a ſpoonfull of Salte, a ſpoonefull of Sinamon, halfe a ſpoonefull of Ginger, foure ſpoonfuls of Roſewater, chop them altogether then make your Tart of fine paſte, and fill it with your ſtuffe: then cloſe it with a couer, and ſtrike vpon the lid of your Tart butter that is molten, and caſt fine ſugar vpon it, as you doe to a Marchpane, let not your Ouen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> too hot for it aſketh but litle baking.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Ho to make a tart of cheeſe</head>
                  <p>MAke your Tart, and then take Banbery Chéeſe, and pare away the out ſide of it and cut the cleane chéeſe in ſmall peeces and put them into the Tart, and when your
<pb facs="tcp:22136:33"/>Tart is full of Chéeſe: then put two hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of ſugar into your Tart vpon your chéeſe, and caſt in it fiue or ſixe ſpoonefuls of Roſewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and cloſe it vp with a couer, and with a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lay ſweet molten Butter vpon it, and fine Sugar, and bake it in a ſoft ouen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a tart of almonds.</head>
                  <p>BLanch almonds and beat them, and ſtrain them fine with good thicke Creame, then put in Sugar and Roſewater, and boyle it thicke, then make your paſte with butter, fair water, and the yolks of two or thrée Egs, and as ſoone as ye haue driuen your paſte, caſt on a litle ſugar, and roſewater, and harden your paſte afore in the Ouen. Then take it out, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it, and ſet in in againe, and let it bake till it be wel, and ſo ſerue it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a tart of Medlers.</head>
                  <p>TAke medlers that be rotten, &amp; ſtraine them the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſet them on a chafingdiſh of coales, and beate it in two yolks of Egges, and let it boile till it be ſomewhat thick: then ſeaſon it with ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Ginger and ſugar, and lay it in paſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a tart of hippes.</head>
                  <p>TAke Hippes, ſlit them, and pick out the ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels: then ſeeth them in white wine, or in faire water, when they bee ſoft ſodden, ſtraine them as thick as you can, and ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22136:33"/>Sinamon, ginger and ſugar, &amp; lay it in paſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a Curde tart.</head>
                  <p>TAke Creame, yolkes of egs, white bread ſéeth them together, then put in a ſawcer full of Roſewater or Malmeſey, and turne it: and put it into a cloath, when all the whey is out, ſtraine it, and put in Sinamon, Ginger, ſalt, and ſugar, then lay it in paſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Lumbardy tarts.</head>
                  <p>TAke béets, chop them ſmall, and to put them grated bread &amp; chéeſe, and mingle them wel in the chopping, take a few cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rans, and a diſhe of ſwéet butter &amp; melt it, then ſtir al theſe in the butter, together with three yolkes of egges, ſinamon, ginger, and ſugar, and make your tart as larg as you will, and fill it with the ſtuffe, bake it, and ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a tart of bread.</head>
                  <p>TAke grated bread and put to it molten but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and a litle Roſewater and ſugar, and the yolks of egs, and put it into your paſte, and bake, and when you ſerue it, cut it in foure quarters and caſt ſugar on it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A tart to prouoke courage either in man or woman,</head>
                  <p>TAke a quart of good wine, and boile therein two Burre rootes ſcraped cleane, two good Quinces, and a potaton roote well pared,
<pb facs="tcp:22136:34"/>and an ounce of Dates, and when all theſe are boiled verie tender, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be drawne through a ſtrainer wine and al, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put in the yolks of eight egs, and the braines of thrée or fower cocke ſparrowes, and ſtraine them into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and a litle roſewater, and ſéeth them all with Sugar, ſinamon and Ginger, and clones and mace, and put in a litle ſwéet butter, and ſet it vpon a chafingdiſh of coales between two platters, &amp; ſo let it boile til it be ſomthing big.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a tart of Gooſeberies.</head>
                  <p>TAke Goſeberies, and perboile them in white or claret win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, or ſtronge ale, and withall boyle a litle white bread: then take them vp &amp; draw them through a ſtrainer as thick as you can with the yolks of ſixe Egges, then ſeaſon it vp with ſugar, and halfe a diſhe of butter, and ſo bake it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Roſted meats.</head>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Allowes of mutton.</head>
                  <p>TAke faire Mutton, and cut it thin in flakes then take faire Parſley, Onions, Yolkes of Egges, ſodden Egges, Marrow, or ſwéet ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, chop al theſe together, and ſo rolle it vp wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the mutton, and roſte it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to roſt a Gybot of mutton.</head>
                  <p>CVt the fleſh of a leg of Mutton, take out the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22136:34"/>bone, and take the fleſh that you cut foorth, and chop it ſmall, and put thereto yolks of Egges, cloues and Mace, Corrans, Roſemarie, Parſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley. Time and ſome ſuet, and mingle them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, and put them into a bag and ſowe it vp, and ſo roſte it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to roſte a Hare.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt waſh it in faire water, then perboile it and lay in cold water againe, then larde it, and roſte it on a broch. Then to make ſauce for it, take red Vinigar, Salt, Pepper, Ginger Cloues, Mace, and put them together. Then mince apples and onions, and frie them in a pan: then put your ſawce to them with a litle ſugar, and let them boyle well together, then baſte it vpon your Hare and ſo ſerue it foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſte a Calues head.</head>
                  <p>MAke a litle hole in the head, &amp; plucke out all the braines, and lay the head to ſoake: then to make a pudding in it, take white bread, and lay it to ſoake in milke, and ſtrain it thicke, then take foure yolkes of Egges, cloues Mace, Pepper, Saffron, corans, Dates, and a good quantitie of Butter, make a good Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and fill the head full: then take the bone, and ſtop the hole, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is almoſt enough, caſt crummes of bread on it: then cleaue it, and make ſawce to it with Synamon, ſugar, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb facs="tcp:22136:35"/>and vinegar, and boyle them al together, and then you may ſerue it foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſt a Capon, Pheſant or partridge.</head>
                  <p>ROſte a capon with his head of, his wings and legges on whole: and your pheſant in like ſort: but when you ſerue him in, ſtick one of his feathers vpon his breaſt: and in lyke maner you muſt roſte a Partridg, but ſtick vp no feather.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to roſte Veniſon.</head>
                  <p>LEt your Veniſon be perboyled, then make it tender, and caſt into it colde water, then Larde it, and roſte it, and for ſauce: take broth vinegar, pepper, cloues and mace, with a little ſalt, and boyle all theſe together, and ſo vppon your veniſon ſerue it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to roſte a quaile.</head>
                  <p>LEt his legs be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and knit one within another, and ſo roſte him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſte a Crane, Heron Curlew or Bitture.</head>
                  <p>ROſte a crane with his legs turned vp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, his winges cut off at the ioynt next the bodie, and then wind the necke about the broch, and put the bill into his breaſt, the Heron Curlew and Bitture, after the ſame maner, but let the Bittures head be off.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:22136:35"/>
                  <head>To roſte a Plouer or a Snite.</head>
                  <p>TAke and roſte a plouer with his head of, and his legges turned vpward vpon his backe, but the Snite with his bill put into his breaſt, and his legges turned vpward vpon his breſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to roſte Woodcocks.</head>
                  <p>PLucke them, and then draw the guts out of them, but leaue the liuer ſtill in them, then ſtuffe them with Larde chopped ſmall, and Iuniper berries, with his bil put into his breſt and his féet as the Snite, and ſo roſte him on a ſpit, &amp; ſet vnder it a faire large pan with white wine in it, &amp; chopped parſley, vinegar, ſalt, and ginger: then make toſtes of white bread, &amp; toſte them vpon a girdion, ſo that they be not burnt: then put theſe toſtes in a diſh, &amp; vpon them lay your woodcocks, and put your ſauce, being the ſame broth vpon them, and ſo ſerue them forth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To ſeeth fiſh.</head>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make fine rice pottage.</head>
                  <p>TAke halfe a pound of Iorden almondes, and half a pound of rice, and a gallo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of running water, and a handfull of oke barke, and let the barke be boyled in the running water, and the almonds beaten with the hulles and al on, and ſo ſtrained to make the rice pottage withal.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make good Lenton pottage.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22136:36"/>
                  <p>TAke Eeles and flea them, and cut them in culpins, and caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a pot of faire water, and take Parſley and Onions, &amp; ſhred them together not to ſmal, &amp; take cloues Mace, powder of Pepper and Synamon, and caſt it thereto, and let them boyle together a white: alſo take a good portion of wine, &amp; thick yeſt, and put it thereto, and let it boyle together a while. Then take ſaffron, ſalt, and Vinegar, and caſt it therto, and ſerue it for good pottage.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to ſeeth a Pike.</head>
                  <p>TAke white wine, faire water, vinegar, and a little yeſt, or els a few gooſeberies, boil theſe together, and before yee ſéeth your Pike, lay it in vinegar and ſalt, this is a good broth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to ſeeth a carpe.</head>
                  <p>YOu muſt take Red wine, and the bloud of the carp, and a litle Vinegar and ſalt, and let it lie in this a while. Then ſeeth your carpe in it, and put pepper halfe broken in it, and a peece of ſweete butter, and make your ſoppes therewith and ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to ſeeth a Gurnard.</head>
                  <p>YOu muſt open your Gurnard in the back, and faire waſh and ſeeth it in water and ſalt, with the fiſhie ſide vpward: and when it is ſodden well, you may take ſome of the beſt of your broth if you will, or els a litle faire wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:22136:36"/>and put to it newe yeſt, a little Vergious, parſlie, Roſemarie, a litle Time, whole Mace and a peece of ſwéet Butter: and let it boyle in a pipkin by it ſelfe till it bee well boyled, and then when you ſerue in your Gurnard, powre the ſame broth vpon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſeeth freſh Salmon.</head>
                  <p>TAke a litle water, and as much Beere and ſalte, and put thereto Parſley, Time, and Roſemarie, and let all theſe boyle togeather. Then put in your Salmon, and make your broth ſharpe with ſome Vinigar.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to ſeeth a Breame.</head>
                  <p>PVt White Wine into a pot and let it ſéeth, then take and cut your Bream in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and put him into the pot: then take an Onion and chop it ſmall, then take Nutmegs beaten, Synamon and Ginger, whole Mace, &amp; a pound of Butter, and let it boyle altogether and ſo ſeaſon it with ſalt, ſerue it vpon ſops, and garniſh it with fruite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſeeth Roches, Flounders, or Eeles.</head>
                  <p>MAke yee good broth with newe Yeaſt, put therein Vergious, Salt, Parſley, a little Time, and not muche Roſemarie and pepper: ſo ſet it on the fire and boyle it, &amp; when it is wel boyled, put in Roches, Flounders, Eeles, and a quantitie of ſwéet butter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22136:37"/>
                  <head>How to ſeeth Stockfiſh.</head>
                  <p>TAke Stockfiſh and water it well, and then put out all the bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e from the fiſhe, then put it into a pipkin, and put in no more water then ſhall couer it, then ſet it on the fire, and as ſoone as it beginneth to boyle on the one ſide, then turne the other ſide to the fire, and as ſoone as it beginneth to boile on the other ſide, take it of and put it into a Colender, and let the water run out from it, and put in ſalte in the boyling of it, and take a little faire water and ſweete butter, and let it boyl in a diſh vntill it be ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thicke, then poure it on the ſtockfiſh, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To ſeeth a Dory or a Mullet.</head>
                  <p>MAke your broth light with yeſt, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſauorie with ſalt, and put therein a little Roſemarie, and when it ſeeths put in your fiſh, and let it ſeeth very ſoftly. Take faire water and vergious a like much, and put thereto a litle new yeaſt, corrans, whole Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and a little Mace, and Dates ſhred verie ſmal, and boyle them wel together: and when they be well boyled, take the beſt of your broth that your fiſh is ſodden in, and put to it ſtrawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, Gooſeberries, or Barberries, ſweete Butter, and ſome ſugar, and ſo ſeaſon vp your broth, and poure vpon your Dorie or Mullet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:22136:37"/>
                  <head>To ſtewe Herrings.</head>
                  <p>TAke ale, and put therin a few onions ſmall cut. &amp; a ſpoonful of Muſtard, great raiſons and ſaffron, &amp; thick it with grated bread: if you will haue puddings in them, take the ſoft roes of the herrings, &amp; ſtamp them with a litle thick almond milke, and put thereto ſome Dates or Figs minced, cloues, mace, Sugar, ſaffron and ſalt, and ſome corrans, and grated bread.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To roſte a peece of Stockfiſh.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quarter of ſtockfiſh and a litle gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bread and a litle creame, &amp; foure yolk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of egs, a few Dates minced with corrans ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, ginger, and a litle pepper, and ſo lay it to the fire &amp; baſte it well with Butter and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigar, &amp; ſome ſinamon and ginger in your but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherewith you baſte it, and ſo ſerue it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To bake fiſh.</head>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make herring pies.</head>
                  <p>TAke herrings and cruſh them in your hands, to ſhall you looſe the fleſh from the ſkin, ſaue the ſkin, as whole as ye can, &amp; ſcrape of all the fiſh, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none be left therupon: then take a pound of almondes, or as manie as ye bee diſpoſed to make, blanch them, and ſtamp them, and in the ſtamping of them, put in one ſoft roe, and one harde rowe, and fiue or ſixe Dates, and a
<pb facs="tcp:22136:38"/>ſpoonfull or two of grated bread, and a pint of Muſcadell to grinde them withall, but ye may not grind them to fine, nor may not make them too moiſt with your muſcadell, but ſomewhat ſtiffe, that you may fill the ſkinnes of your He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings: Then take Roſewater, and a little ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron to colour Almondes withall, when yee haue ground them. Then put in foure Dates and cut them fine, and a handfull of Currans, and a litle ſugar, then make fine paſte, and rol it as thinne as you can, and ſtrewe thereon a good deale of ſugar, then put your Herrings therin, and bake them</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake a Carpe.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the ſcales, and take foorth the Gall, and with cloues, Mace, and ſalte, ſeaſon it and take corans and prunes, and put about the carpe, and take butter and put it vpon him and let him bake two houres.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake a ioll of freſh Salmon.</head>
                  <p>TAke Ginger and ſalt, and ſeaſon it, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine currans, and caſt them about and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, and let the paſte be fine, and take a litle Butter and lay about it in the paſte, and ſet it in the ouen two houres, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake a Breame.</head>
                  <p>SCale it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and take cloues, Mace, and ſalte, and put it in fine paſte. Then take corans
<pb facs="tcp:22136:38"/>and ſet about it, and a good quanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ter, and put it into the belly of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> about it: let it bake two houres.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake a Gurnard with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke certaine Eeles and a Gurna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> them into your Coffin, &amp; take cloues <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and ſalt, and caſte a litle into the boff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> your coffin. Then take the Eeles and lay them about the Gurnarde, and the reſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of pour ſpice caſt about it, and take a quantitie of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans and Prunes, let it bake thrée houres.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to bake a trout.</head>
                  <p>WAſh it a litle, and take two or three Eles, a few Cloues, mace, ginger, and Salt, and ſeaſon the Trout and the Eeles to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and put them in the coffin together and a few Corrans about it, and a quantitie of but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let them bake an houre and a halfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a good marchpane.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, take a pound of long ſmal almonds, blanch them in colde water. Then take a cloth and dry them as dry as you can The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtamp them ſmall, and put no liquor to them but as you muſt needes to keepe them from oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and that litle that ye put to them muſt be Roſewater, in like maner you ſhould but wet your Peſtels end therin, for feare of putting too
<pb facs="tcp:22136:39"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uor therin: and when you haue beaten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, take half a pound of ſugar or more, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e beaten to ſmal powder, but it muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>gar, &amp; then in put it to your Almondes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> them altogether, when they be bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake your wafers and cut them compoſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the bigneſſe that you will haue your Marchpane of. Then ſo ſoone as you can after the tempering of the ſtuffe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it be put in paſte of wafers, and ſtrik in abroad with a flat ſtick of wood as euen as you can, and pinch the very ſtuffe as if it were an edge ſet on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, put a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vnder it, &amp; then ſet it vpon a fair board and lay a Lattine baſon vppon it the bottome vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Then lay burning coales vpon the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of your baſon, and euer anon lift vp your baſon to ſée how it baketh: and if it happen to be browne, or to brown too faſt in ſome places fold paper as broade as that place is, and this well tended, ye ſhal bake one in litle more then three quarters of an houre: when it is baked, put on your gold and your biſkets, and ſtick in long comfets, and then ſhall yee make a good Marchpane: But before that ye bake it, yee muſt caſt on it fine ſugar and Roſewater, and that wil make him to criſpe like vnto yſe, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you muſt haue a hoope for to make your Marchpane in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22136:39"/>
                  <head>To make good Reſtons.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quart of fine flower, lay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>boord, and make a hole in the mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lower with your hand, and put a ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>le Yeſt therein, and ten yolkes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> put thereto two ſpoonefuls of Sinamo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> one of Ginger, and a ſpoonefull of cloue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Mace and a quarterne of Sugar fine beate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a litle ſaffron, and halfe a ſpoonefull of Salt. Then take a diſhfull of Butter, melt it and put into your flower, and therwithal make your paſte as it were for manchets, and mould it a good while and cut it in peeces the bignes of Ducks egges, and ſo moulde euerie péece as a manchet, and make them after the faſhion of an ackorn broad aboue, and narrow beneath Then ſet them in an Ouen, and let them bake thrée quarters of an howre. Then take fiue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of butter and clarif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie it clean vpon a ſoft fire: then drawe foorth your Reſtons foorth of the Ouen, and ſcrape the bottoms of them faire and cut them ouerthwart in foure péeces, and put them in a faire charger, and put your clari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied butter vpon them. Then haue powder of Synamon and Ginger readie by you, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar verie fine: and mingle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> altogether, and euer as you ſet your peeces thence, togeather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſt ſome of your ſugar, Sinamon &amp; ginger vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:22136:40"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> when you haue ſet them al vp, lay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> faire platter, and put a litle butter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and caſt a litle ſugar vpon them, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>em in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a Vaunt.</head>
                  <p>TAke marow of Beefe, as muche as you can hold in both your hands, cut it as big as great dice. Then take ten Dates, cut them as big as ſmal dice: then take thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie prunes, and cut the fruite from the ſtones, then take halfe a handfull of Corrans waſhe them and picke them, then put your marrow in a cleane platter, and your dates, prunes, and Corrans: then take ten yolks of Egs, and put into your ſtuffe afore rehearſed. Then take a quarterne of ſugar, and more, and beat it ſmal and put to your marrow. Then take two ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of Sinamon, and a ſpoonful of ſugar, and put them to your ſtuffe, and mingle them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, then take eight yolks of egs, and foure ſpoonfuls of Roſewater, ſtrain them, and put a litle ſugar to it. Then take a fayre frying pan, and put a litle péece of butter in it, as much as a Walnut, and ſet it on a good fyre, and when it looketh almoſt blacke, put it out of your pan, and as faſt as you can, put halfe of the yolks of Egs, into the midſt of your pan, and let it run all the bredth of your pan, and frie it faire and
<pb facs="tcp:22136:40"/>yellowe, and when it is fryed, put it in a fair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſh, and put your ſtuffe therein and ſpread it a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the bottom of the diſh and then make another vaunt euen as you made the other, and ſet it v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a faire bord, and cut it in faire ſlices, of the breadth of your litle finger, as long as your Vaunt is: then lay it vpon your ſtuffe after the faſhion of a lattice window, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cut off the ends of them, as much as lyeth without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward compaſſe of the diſh. Then ſet the diſhe within the Ouen or in a baking pan, and let it bake with leiſure, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is baked enough the marrow will come faire out of the vaunt, vnto the brim of the diſh. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> draw it out, and caſt theron a litle ſugar, and ſo you may ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Frians.</head>
                  <p>TAke thrée handfull of flower, ſeuen yolkes of egges, and halfe a diſhe of Butter, make your paſte therwith, and make two Chew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets therof, as you would make two tarts, and when it is driuen verie fine with your rolling pin, then cut them in péeces of the bigneſſe of your hand. Then take a quartern of ſugar, and one ounce and foure ſpoonfuls of ſinamon, and halfe a ſpoonfull of Ginger, and mingle them altogether, then take lumps of marrow, of the quantitie of your finger, and put it on your pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:22136:41"/>of paſte afore rehearſed, and put vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>poonfuls of your ſugar and ſpices: then take a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itle water and wet your paſte therewith: then make them euen as ye would make a paſtie of Veniſon: then prick them with a pin, and frie them as ye frie fritters, when they be fried, caſt a litle ſugar on them, and ſo ſerue them in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make frians in Lent.</head>
                  <p>TAke Valſome Eeles and ſée they be fat, and cut the fiſh from the bone, and mince it ſmal and a Warden or two with it. Then ſeaſon it with Pepper, ſalt, cloues, mace, and Saffron: then put to it corrans, Dates, and Prunes, ſmal minced, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your fruit is altogether then poure on a litle Vergious and cut it in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle péeces, and ſo bake it. &amp; put a péece of But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the midſt of the péeces to make it moyſt, ſo cloſe it, and bake it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Snowe.</head>
                  <p>TAke a quart of thicke cream, and fiue or ſixe whites of egs, a ſawcerfull of Sugar, and a ſawcerfull of Roſewater, beate altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and euer as it riſeth take it out with a ſpoone: then take a loafe of bread, cut away the cruſt, and ſet it vpright in a platter Then ſet a faire great Roſemarie buſhe in the middeſt of your bread: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lay your ſnow with a ſpoon vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your reſemary, &amp; vpon your bread, &amp; gilt it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22136:41"/>
                  <head>To make a good Gellie.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, take foure Calues féete, and ſcald o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the haire of them: then ſeeth them in fair<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> water til they be tender. Then take out your féet, and let your broth ſtand till it be cold: then ye ſhall take of clean the féete from it, and then put Claret wine and a litle Malmeſey to it: it ye haue a pottel of Gellie water: then put to it a quart of wine, and a pint of Malmeſey, then ſeaſon it with ſalt, and put therto one pound of Sugar, one ounce of Ginger, one ounce and a halfe of Sinamon, twelue cloues, twelue pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cornes, and a litle Saffron, ſo boile all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: then take a good ſawcerful of Vinegar and lay your turnfall therein: and then put it to your Gellie, til it be ſomwhat kéeled, then put in your whites of egs, and let al theſe boil together. Then ſet all theſe by, and within a while let it run through your bag.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Gellie both white and red.</head>
                  <p>TAke foure Calues feete, ſcalde them verie cleane, and cut them in the middeſt, and as néere as ye can, take away al the fat clean out of the ioints, and let the féete lie in faire water foure or fiue houres, &amp; change the waters often. Then take a clean pot, and put your feete in it: and put to them thrée quarts of fair water, and
<pb facs="tcp:22136:42"/>ſcum it verie cleane, euer as any fat doeth riſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et it bee taken away, and ſo let it ſeeth till the third part of your liquor be ſodden away, and your feet very tender, then take it from the fire and let the liquor run through a ſtrainer into a faire earthen pan, and ſet the pan in ſome cold place that it may be ſtiffe; and when it is ſtiffe take a ſharp knife and cut away the vppermoſt of the gellie as thin as you can, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deuide your gellie in the pan, &amp; put it in two earthen pots: take thrée ounces of ſinamon large, and waſh it verie cleane: then breake it of the bigneſſe of a penie. Take of caſe Ginger almoſt an ounce and pare it cleane, then cut it as much as if you would eat it with figs: then take two nutmegs and cut them in four or fiue peeces: and put all this in one of your pots, and put therto a pound of Sugar, as ye thinke good, and put thereto a ſawcerfull of white Viniger, and a litle fayre white ſalt, faire picked, and very clean: then ſet your pot in a ſoft fire, and ſo let it ſtew but not ſéeth, and let the pot be couered verie cloſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it hath ſtued a while, with a ſpoone aſſay it whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther it be flaſhy in the mouth, if it be, put in a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more Sinamon, and if it be hot of the ſpice, put in a pint of white wine, and let it ſtew a while. Then take the pot from the fire, and let it ſtand till it be betwéen hot and cold, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:22136:42"/>the whites of ten Egs, and beat them well, and put them into the pot, but ſee that your liquor be not too hot, nor too cold, when you put them in. Then ſet your pot to the fire againe, &amp; when the Egs be hardened, with a ſpoone take them cleane off, and ſet the pot from the fire, ere yes take of the whites. Then haue your gelly bag clean, and hang it in a fair place, and put in the bottome of your bag a litle Margeram, and ſo let it run through your bag thrée or foure times or more if neede require, but keepe alwaies a cleane cloth ouer the mouth of your bag, then caſt your diſhes, when all is runne out, be wel ware ye haue no duſt when it runneth, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhal caſt it, and haue a litle fire beſide your bagge, when it is running, make your red gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of your other pot, and ſeaſon it as ye did the white gellie, and doo thereto in the putting in of the Egs as yee did before. But for the Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs ye muſt take twentie cloues bruiſed, and beware ye make not too deep a colour of your Turneſal at the firſt, but take of it by litle and litle at once, and put in the bottome of your bag a litle Roſemary, &amp; ſo vſe it els in euerie thing as ye vſed the white.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make gellie with fleſh.</head>
                  <p>TAke knuckles of Veal, and cut the ioints al to peeces, and lay them in faire water the
<pb facs="tcp:22136:43"/>ſpace of an houre, then waſh them cleane, and lay them in faire water again the ſpace of half an houre. Then take a faire pot and put your fleſh in it: then fill your pot with Claret wine and water, and ſet it to the fire, and ſcum it as clean as ye can: then let it boyle as ſoftly as ye can, for the ſooner it is boyled the longer it wil bee ere it come to a Gellie: therefore it muſt boyle but ſoftlye, when it is boyled, ſtraine the liquor into a fair boll, and when it is cold, take off the greace that lyeth vpon it: then take of the cléereſt of the ſtuffe, and put it in a faire pot and ſeeth it, and then put in your Sugar: then take Synamon, graines, cloues, long Pepper, Nutmegs and ginger, of each of theſe a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, then bruiſe them, and ſearce out the ſmal ſpices, and put the greateſt into your pot, when it boyleth, put in whites of Egs beaten: Then take a Scummer and ſcum them as they riſe, and drie your Turneſall by the fyre, and rub it cleane, and colour your Gellie therewith, then take your bag, and put Roſemarie in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of it, and hang it by the fire ſide, and let your gellie runne two times through your bag into a faire veſſell.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make gellie with fiſh.</head>
                  <p>TAke Tenches and ſcalde them, and drawe them and waſh them cleane: then put your
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:22136:43"/>Tenches into a fair pot: then take white wine or claret and fill your pot therewith: then take Iſenbras as much as ye think beſt. Then take your pot and ſet it on the fire, and let it boyl the ſpace of an hower and a half: then take it from the fire, and let your liquor run through a ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, then let your liquor ſtand till it bee colde. Then order it in euerie point as yee did the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before that is made with fleſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>All neceſſaries apperteyning to a Banquet.</head>
                  <p>SYnamon, Sugar, Nutmegs, Pepper, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, Saunders, Coleander, Anniſeeds, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coras, al kind of Comfets, Orenges, Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granate, Torneſall, Lemmons, Prunes, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, Barberries conſerued, Paper white and browne: ſeeds, Roſewater Raiſons, Rie flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Ginger, Cloues and mace, Damaſk water, Dates, Cherries conſerued, ſweete Orenges, Wafers for your Marchpanes, ſeaſoned and vnſeaſoned Spinnedges.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make a Tyſſan.</head>
                  <p>TAke a pinte of Barley beeing picked, ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled with faire water, ſo put it in a faire ſtone morter, and with your peſtel rub the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,
<pb facs="tcp:22136:44"/>and that will make it tuſke, then pick out the barley from the huſkes, and ſet your barley on the fire in a gallon of faire water, ſo let it ſeeth til it come to a pottell: then put into your water, Succory, Endiue, Cinkefoyle, violet leaues, of each one handfull, one ounce of anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, one ounce of liquoris bruiſed, and thirtie great raiſons, ſo let all this geare ſeeth till it come to a quart: then take it of, let it ſtand and ſettle, and ſo take of the cleareſt of it, and let it be ſtrained, and when you haue ſtrained the cleareſt of it, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let it ſtand a good pretie while. Then put in foure whites of Egs al to beaten, ſhels and all, then ſtir it well together, ſo ſet it on the fire againe, let it ſeeth, and euer as the ſcum dooth riſe take it of, and ſo let it ſéeth a while: then let it run through a ſtrainer or an Ipocras bagge, and drink of it in the morning warme.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to clarifie Whey.</head>
                  <p>TAke the iuyce of Fumetorie, halfe a pint of the iuice of Borage, of Endiue, of the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of hoppes, of each of them a quarter of a pinte, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put al theſe iuices to a pottle of whey with three whites of Egges beaten, and with Sugar ſufficient: then boyle them on an eaſy fire, take away the ſcum of it as it riſeth, and when it is cold let it run through a fayre ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22136:44"/>take thereof euery morning halfe a pinte, and before ſupper as much: this wil pure your blood, and wil continue good foure daies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make fillets Gallantine.</head>
                  <p>TAke faire Pork, and take of the ſkin and roſte it halfe enough, then take it off the ſpit, and ſmite it in faire peeces, and caſt it in a faire pot: then cut Onions, but not too ſmall, and frie them in faire ſuet, put them into the Porke, then take the broth of Beefe or Mutton and put thereto, and ſet them on the fyre, and put thereto powder of Pepper, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, cloues and Mace, and let them boil well together. Then take faire bread and Vinigar, &amp; ſtéepe the bread with ſome of the ſame broth, ſtraine it, and ſome bloud withall, or els ſaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and colour it with that, and let all boyle together, then caſt in a litle Saffron, and ſalte, and then may you ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Gallantine.</head>
                  <p>TAke toſtes of white bread, boile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on a chafingdiſh of coals, with vinigar whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it hath ſoked afore in the vinigar, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boiling put in a branch of Roſemarie, Sugar, Synamon and Ginger, ſtraine it, and ſerue it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make toſtes of Veale.</head>
                  <p>TAke the kidneyes, choppe them verie ſmall, then put to it foure or fiue yolkes of Egges,
<pb facs="tcp:22136:45"/>three ſpoonefull of ſugar, a little ſynamon and Ginger, a ſpoonefull of Corrans cleane wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and picked, choppe them altogeather, then make ſops of ſtale white breade, and lay your ſtuffe vpon them, and take a frying pan and a diſh of ſweet Butter in it, and melt it: then put in your toſts and frie them vpon a ſoft fire: then lay them in a diſh, and caſt ſugar on them, your fire muſt be verie ſoft, or els they will burne.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make an apple moyſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke apples, and cut them in two or four peeces, boyle them till they bee ſoft, and bruiſe them in a morter, and put thereto the yolks of two Egs, and a litle ſwéet butter, ſet them on a chafingdiſh of coales, and boyle them a little, and put thereto a litle Sugar, ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon and ginger, and ſo ſerue them in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Peſcods.</head>
                  <p>MAke your paſt with fine flower, &amp; yolkes of Egs, make it ſhort and driue it thinne.</p>
                  <p>Then take Dates, Corrans &amp; marrowe, and cut them like Dice, and ſeaſon them with ſalt becauſe of the marrow a litle: then put in Synamon, ſugar and Ginger, make your paſt as you do for the Frians in Butter or ſuet, and ſerue them in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make peſcods another way.</head>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:22136:45"/>
                  <p>TAke apples, and mince them ſmall, take Figs, Dates, Corans; great Raiſons, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Ginger, and Sugar, mince them, and put them all together, and make them in lytle flat peeces, and fry them in butter and Oyle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Pettie ſeruices.</head>
                  <p>TAke faire flower, Saffron and ſugar, make thereof paſte, and make thereof coffins, and take the yolkes of Egs tried from the whites, and ſee the yolks be all whole. Then lay three or foure egs in the coffin, and two or three pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of marrow: then take powder of Ginger, ſugar and corrans, and roll the marrow in it, and put all in the pie, and couer it, or bake it in a pan.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Spaniſh balles.</head>
                  <p>TAke a péece of a leg of Mutton, and pare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſkin from the fleſh, chop the fleſh very ſmall: then take marrow of beefe, and cut it as big as a haſell nut, &amp; take as much of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in quantity as yee haue of fleſh, &amp; put both in a fair platter and ſome ſalt, and eight yolks of egs, and ſtirre them wel together: then take a litle earthen pot, and put in it a pint and a halfe of beefe broth that is not ſalt, or elſe Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton broth and make it ſeeth: then make balles of your ſtuffe, and put them in boyling broth
<pb facs="tcp:22136:46"/>one after another, and let them ſtewe ſoftly the ſpace of two houres, Then lay them on ſopps three or foure in a diſh, and of the vppermoſt of the broth vpon the ſops, and make your balles as big as tennis balles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make balles of Italie.</head>
                  <p>TAke a peece of a legge of Veale, perboyle it, then pare away al the ſkin and ſinews, and chop the Veale very ſmall, a litle ſalt and pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per two yolks of Egges hard roſted, and ſeuen yolks raw, temper all theſe with your Veale, then make balles thereof as big as Walnuts, and boyle them in beefe broth, or mutton broth as ye did the other before rehearſed, and put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your broth ten beaten cloues, a race of Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, a litle Vergious, foure or fiue lumpes of marrowe whole, let them ſtew the ſpace of an houre: then ſerue them vpon ſops, eight or nine in a diſh, and betwixt the balles you muſt laye the lumps of marrow.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make almond butter after the beſt and neweſt maner.</head>
                  <p>TAke a pound of almonds or more as ye wil, blanch them in cold water, or in warme, as ye may haue leyſure: after the blanching, let them lie an houre in cold water: then ſtampe them in fair cold water as fine as ye can: then put your almondes in a cloth, and gather your
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:22136:46"/>cloth round vp in your hands, and preſſe out the milke as much as you can, if ye thinke they be not ſmal enough, beat them againe, and ſo get out milke as long as you can. Then ſet it on the fire, and when it is ready to ſéeth, put in a good quantitie of Salt, and Roſewater, that will turne it, and after that it is in, let it haue one boyling, and then take it from the fire, and caſte it abroad vpon a linnen cloth, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the cloth, ſcrape off the whey as long as it will runne. Then ſcrape together the butter into the midſt of your cloth, and binde the cloth together, and let it hang ſo long as it will drop Then take péeces of Sugar, as much as yee think will make it ſwéet, and put therto Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water a litle, as much as wil melt the Sugar, and fine pouder of ſaffron, as ye think wil col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour it, and let both your Sugar and Saffron ſtéepe together in that litle quantitie of Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, &amp; with that ſeaſon vp your butter when you wil make it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Ipocras.</head>
                  <p>TAke of choſen Sinamon two ounces, of fine Ginger one ounce, of graines half an ounce of Nutmegs half an ounce, bruiſe them al, and ſtampe them in thrée or foure pintes of good o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differous wine, with a pound of Sugar, by the ſpace of four and twenty houres: then put them
<pb facs="tcp:22136:47"/>into an Ipocras bag of woollen, and ſo receiue the liquor. The readieſt and beſt way is to put the ſpices with the pound of Sugar, &amp; the wine into a bottel, or a ſtone pot ſtopped cloſe, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter xxiiii houres it wil be ready, then caſt a thin linnen cloth, and letting ſo much run through as ye wil occupie at once, and kéepe the veſſell cloſe, for it will ſo well kéepe both the ſpirite, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and vertue of the wine, and alſo ſpices.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Ipocras another way.</head>
                  <p>TAke a gallon of wine, an ounce of ſinamon two ounces of ginger, one pound of Sugar, twentie cloues bruiſed, and twentie cornes of pepper big beaten, let all theſe ſoake together one night &amp; then let it run through a bag, and it will be good Ipocras.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Egs vpon ſops.</head>
                  <p>TAke Egs and potch them as ſoft as ye can, then take a fine manchet, and make ſoppes therof, and put your ſops in a diſh, and put ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious thereto and Sugar, and a litle Butter: then ſet it to the fire, and let it boile: then take your egs and lay them vpon your ſops, and caſt a litle chopt Parſlie vppon them, and ſo ſerue them in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Egs in Lent.</head>
                  <p>TAke Hennes Egges, and put out cleane the white and the yolke. Then waſh your ſhel
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:22136:47"/>clean, and take almond milk, and ſéeth it with Iſanglas, or of the broth of a Pike or a Tench, and when it is ſodden, take it off, but before yée take it from the fire, ye muſt ſeaſon it with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and ſalt, and fill your egge ſhels before the milke be cold. Then make a hole in the Egge aboue, and cut out ſo much of the white as yee wil make your yolks, then colour your mylke that he left afore with Saffron, like the yolk of an egge, and fill vp the hole againe therewith, and let it ſtand til it be occupied.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make caſte creame.</head>
                  <p>TAke milke as it commeth from the Cow, a quart or leſſe, and put thereto raw yolks of Egges, temper the milke and the egges toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Then ſet them ſo tempered vpon a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingdiſh of coales, and ſtirre it ſtill and put ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar to it, and ſée it curd not, and it will be like creame of Almonds: when it is boyled thicke enough, then caſte a litle ſugar on it, and ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle Roſewater vpon it, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make caſte Creame another way.</head>
                  <p>TAke the milke that is milked ouer night, &amp; ſcum off the Cream, then take the milk and ſixe whites of egs, ſtraine them together, and two yolks of egs mingled together, and boyle them altogether vntill they turn to a Curds, then put thereto a quantitie of Virgious,
<pb facs="tcp:22136:48"/>and then it will turne: then take the ſame, and put it in a linnen cloth, and hang it vpon a pin a litle while, &amp; let the whay run from it. Then take it downe and ſtraine it into a platter, and ſeaſon it with a litle Roſewater and Sugar, and ſo ſerue it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make clowted Cream after Miſtres Horſmans way.</head>
                  <p>WHen you haue taken the milke from the Kine, ſtraight ſet it on the fire, but ſee that your fire bee without ſmoake, and ſoft fire, and ſo kéepe it on from morning tell it be night or nigh therabout, and ye muſte be ſure that it doth not ſéeth all that while, and ye muſt let your milke be ſet on the fire, in as broad a veſſell as you can. Then take it from the fire, and ſet it vpon a boord, and let it ſtand al night: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the morning take off the cream and put it in a diſh, or where ye wil.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Creame of Almonds.</head>
                  <p>TAke thick Almond milke, and ſéeth it a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, then take it from the fire, and corne it with ſalt and vinigre. Then caſt it in a cloth, and with a litle knife ſcrape in vnder the cloth and there will come out whey. Then put the Creame together in the midſt of the cloth, and hang it on a pin, and let more whey drop out til ye thinke it be well. Then put it in a veſſell,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:22136:48"/>and put to it ſugar plentie, if it hange too long that it be too drie: then temper it with ſwéete wine, and dreſſe it if you wil with ſmal raiſins and lay it like morterels, or els put it abroad, and lay borage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aues vpon it, or els red com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fets and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a good poſſet curde.</head>
                  <p>TAke your milk and ſet it on the fire, and ſet it ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th put in yolks of egs according to the quantity of your milk: but ſee that your egs be tempered with ſome of the milke ere y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> put the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to the milke that is on the fire or els it will fall together and mar all, and yée muſt ſtirre it ſtil til it ſéeth and begin to ryſe. Then take it off from the fire, but before yée take it off, haue your drinke ready in a fair ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, on a chafingdiſh of coales, and powre the milk into the baſon as it ſtandeth ouer the cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fingdiſh w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re, ſo couer it, &amp; let it ſtand a while Then take it vp and caſt on Sinamon and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>Miſtreſſe Drakes way to make ſoft Cheeſe all the yeere through, that it ſhall be like rowen Cheeſe.</head>
                  <p>TAke your milke as it commeth from the Cow, and put it in a veſſell til it be cold, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake as much faire water, and ſet it on the fire whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your water is warm, put ſo much of your
<pb facs="tcp:22136:49"/>water is warm, put ſo much of your water in that milk as wil warme the milk. Then take a ſpoonefull of runnet and more, and put into your milke, and make your Chéeſe, and put it into a faire cloth, and ſo put it into the preſſe, &amp; turne it in the preſſe often, and wipe it wyth faire clothes, as often as ye turne it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Fritters.</head>
                  <p>TAke a pinte of Ale, and foure yolkes of Egges, and a litle ſaffron, a ſpooneful of Cloues and mace, and a litle ſalte, and halfe a handfull of ſugar, put all this in a faire plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſtirre them all together with a ſpoone, and make your batter thereof. Then take ten Apples, pare and cut them as big as a groate, put them in your batter: then take your ſuet &amp; ſet it on the fire, &amp; when it is hot, put your bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; your apples to your ſuet with your hande one by one, and when they be faire and yellow take them out, and lay them in a faire platter, and let them ſtand a litle while by the fire ſide Then take a fair platter, and lay your fritters therein and caſte a litle ſugar on them, and ſo ſerue them in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Curde Fritters.</head>
                  <p>TAke the yolks of ten Egs, and breake ſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a pan, &amp; put to them one handfull of Curds and one handful of fine flower, and ſtraine th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:22136:49"/>all together, and make batter, and if it be not thicke enough, put more Curdes in it, and ſalt to it. Then ſet it on the fire in a frying panne, with ſuch ſtuffe as ye will fry them with, and when it is hot, with a ladle take part of your batter, and put of it into your panne, and let it run as ſmal as you can, &amp; ſtir the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a ſtick and turne them with a ſcummer, &amp; when they be faire and yellow fryed, take them out, &amp; c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt ſugar vpon them, and ſerue them foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Fritters with marrow.</head>
                  <p>TAke thrée handfuls of fine flower and more and lay it in a faire platter, and put thereto ſixe yolks of Egs and almoſt a pint of ale, and a good handful of Sugar, and two ſpoonfuls of Sinamon, and a ſpoonful of Ginger, and halfe a ſpoonefull of cloues and mace, a little ſalte, and a litle ſaffron to collour it withall. Then take a ſpoone, and ſtir all theſe for ſaid things together: and make your batter therewith: then take your marrow, and cut it of the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a groat: then haue a frying pan readie with ſwéet ſuet therein, and ſet it to the fyre, and when it is hot dip your marrow in the but<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, and put it into the pan péece by peece, and euer be ſtiring them with a ſtick, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be fryed, take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of your pan with a ſcum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and lay them in a faire platter, and take
<pb facs="tcp:22136:50"/>Sugar, Sinamon and Ginger, and caſt vpon them, and ſo ſerue them in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Stocke Frittors.</head>
                  <p>TAke a handful of Marrow, or the kidneyes of a Calfe, chop them ſmall. Then take ten yolks of egs and put them in your marrow or kidne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es. Then take a handfull of Corrans, and waſh them cleane, put them to your ſtuffe and take ten dates and cut them ſmal, and put them to your ſtuffe, and take two handfull of grated, bread, two ſpoonful of Ginger, and one ſpoonfull of ſinamon, and a ſpoonfull of cloues and mace a quarter of Sugar and a litle Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and mingle your ſpices and ſtuffe together in a fair platter: then take two handful of fine flower, and ſixe yolks of egges, and make your batter therwith with ale and Saffron. Then make of your ſtuffe afore rehearſed litle pilles as bigge as a walnut. Then haue a frying pan readie with fair ſuet therein vpon the fire, and when it is hot dip your pilles into your batter, and put them into your frying pan, &amp; fry them as ye would frie frittors, and that done, put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a platter, and caſt a litle Sinamon, Sugar, and Ginger on them, and ſo ſerue them in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make Frittors with Apples.</head>
                  <p>TAke fine flower, and temper it with Butter and a litle ſalt, and make a batter, and take
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:22136:50"/>a very litle ſaffron to colour your batter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and when your batter is made, ſtraine it through a ſtrainer, then cut your apples of the bignes of a groat, and put them to your batter then put your ſuet to the fire, and when it is hot, put a peece of your apples to your ſuet, and if it riſe quicklie, then your ſtuffe is well ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, if it abide in the bottome, then it is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> halfe enough: therfore when it riſeth from the bottome, fill pour pan one after another as faſt as ye can, and when they are faire coloured, take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out with a ſcummer, and put them in a platter, and alwaies whiles they are in the pan ſtirre them with a ſtick, and looke that ye haue liquor enough. Then take your frittors, and put them in a fair platter, and then ſcrape Sugar enough vpon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make frittors of ſpinage.</head>
                  <p>TAke a good deale of Spinage, and waſh it cleane, and boyle it in faire water, and when it is boyled, put it in a collender, &amp; let it coole. Then wring all the water out of it as nere as ye can, lay it vpon a board, and chop it with the back of a chopping knife very ſmal and put it in a platter, and put to it four whites of Egs, and two yolks, and the crums of half a manchet grated, and a litle ſinamon and gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſtirre them wel together with a ſpoon
<pb facs="tcp:22136:51"/>and take a frying pan and a diſh of ſwéet But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in it, when it is molten put handſomely in your pan halfe a ſpoonful of your ſtuffe, and ſo beſtowe the reſt after, frye them on a ſoft fire, and turn them when time is, lay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and caſt ſugar on them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Pancakes.</head>
                  <p>TAke new thicke Creame a pint, foure or fiue yolks of egs, a good handfull of flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and two or thrée ſpoonefuls of ale, ſtrain them together into a faire platter, and ſeaſon it with a good handfull of ſugar, a ſpooneful of Synamon, and a litte Ginger: then take a fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pan, and put in a litle peece of Butter, as big as your thombe, and when it is molten brown, caſt it out of your pan, and with a ladle put to the further ſide of your pan ſome of your ſtuffe, and hold your pan aſlope, ſo that your ſtuffe may run abroad ouer all the pan as thin as may be: then ſet it to the fire, and let the fyre be verie ſoft, and when the one ſide is ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, then turn the other, and bake them as dry as ye can without burning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make good white puddings.</head>
                  <p>SEe that your liuers bee not too much par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yled. Then take of the liuers and lights, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ye let them be picked &amp; chopped with kniues, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>n ſtamp them in a morter, &amp; ſtraine them
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:22136:51"/>through a Collender, and put ſome milk to it, to help to get it through, then put foure or fiue Egs and but fiue whites, and put in crums of bread, Cloues, Mace, Saffron Salt, and ſome Pepper, and ſweet ſuet ſmall minced, and let there be enough of it, and ſo ſtill fill them vp, and to black puddings, otemeale, milk &amp; ſalt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Puddings.</head>
                  <p>TAke grated bread, the yolks of ſixe egs, a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Synamon and Salt, Corrans, one min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Date and the ſuet of mutton minced ſmal, knead all theſe together, and make them vp in litle ball<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, boyle them on a chafingdiſh with a little Butter and Vinigar, caſt Synamon and ſugar thereon, and ſo ſerue them in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make Iſing puddings.</head>
                  <p>TAke a platter full of otemeale grotes clean picked, and put thereto of the beſt Creame ſodden that ye can get, blood warme, as much as ſhall couer the grotes, and ſo let them lye and ſoake three houres, or ſome what more, till they haue drunke vp the cream, and the grotes ſwollen and ſoft withall. Then take ſixe egges whites and yolkes, and ſtraine them faire into your grotes: then take one platterful and a half of beefe ſuet, the ſkin cleane pulled from it, and as ſmall minced as is poſſible So that when yee haue minced it, you muſt largelie haue
<pb facs="tcp:22136:52"/>one platterfull and a halfe, &amp; rather more than leſſe: then mingle theſe wel among your groſs then ſeaſon them with ſome ſalt and ſome ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron: &amp; if ye will put in cloues and mace: then fill your Puddings but not too ful, and ſée they be faire waſhed and ſweet, and beware ye pull not away too much of the fat within, for the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they be within, the better it is for the pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings: alſo if ye finde too much creame left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the grotes, after they haue line foure houres: then put out part of it, and ſo ſeeth vp your puddings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a tanſey.</head>
                  <p>TAke a litle Tanſey, Fetherfew, parſley, and Violets, and ſtampe them all together, and ſtraine them with the yolkes of eight or tenne Egges, and three or foure whites, &amp; ſome Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and put thereto ſugar and ſalt, and frie it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a tanſey another way.</head>
                  <p>TAke halfe a handful of Tanſey, of the yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt ye can get, and a handfull of yong bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, ſtrawberry leaues, Lettice, and Violet leaues, and waſh them cleane, and beat them very ſmall in a morter: then put to them eight Egges whites and all, and ſixe yolks beſides, and ſtraine them all together through a ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: then ſeaſon it with a good handfull of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:22136:52"/>and a Nutmeg beaten ſmall. Then take a frying pan, and halfe a diſh of ſweet Butter, and melt it: then put your Egs to it, ſet it on the fire, and with a ſawcer, or with a ladle, ſtir them till they be half baked: then put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a platter, and all to beate them ſtill till they be very ſmall: then take your frying pan made cleane, and put a diſh of ſweet butter in it, and melt it: then put your ſtuffe into your pan by a ſpoonefull at once, and when the one ſide is fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, turn them and fry them together: then take them out, lay them in a platter, and ſcrape ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar on them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make a tanſey in Lent.</head>
                  <p>TAke all maner of hearbs, and the ſpawn of a Pike, or of any other fiſh, and blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched almonds, and a few crums of bread and a little faire water and a pinte of Roſewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and mingle altother, and make it not too thin, and frie it in in Oyle, and ſo ſerue it in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>The making of fine manchet.</head>
                  <p>TAke halfe a buſhell of fine flower twiſe boulted, and a gallon of faire luke warm water, almoſt a handfull of white ſalte, &amp; almoſt a pinte of yeſt, then temper all theſe together, without anis more liquour, as hard as ye can handle it: then let it lie half an
<pb facs="tcp:22136:53"/>hower, then take it vp, and make your Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chetts, and let them ſtand almoſt an hower in the ouen Memorandum, that of euery buſhel of meale may be made fiue and twenty caſt of bread, and euerie loafe to way a pound beſide the cheſill.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>The making of manchets after my Ladie Graies way.</head>
                  <p>TAke two pecks of fine flower, which muſt be twiſe boulted, if you will haue your manchet very faire: Then lay it in a place where ye doe vſe to lay your dowe for your bread, and make a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itle hole in it, and take a quart of fair water blood warme, and put in that water as much leauen as a crab, or a pretie big apple, and as much white ſalt as will into an Egſhell, and all to breake your leuen in the water, and put into your flower halfe a pinte of good ale yeſt, and ſo ſtir this liquor among a litle of your flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, ſo that ye muſt make it but thin at the firſt meeting, and then couer it with flower, and if it be in the winter, ye muſt keep it very warm and in ſummer it ſhall not need ſo much heate, for in the Winter it will not riſe without warmeth. Thus let it lie two howers and a halfe: then at the ſecond opening take more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor as ye thinke will ſerue to wet al the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Then put in a pinte and a halfe of good yeſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:22136:53"/>and ſo all to breake it in ſhort peeces, after yee haue well laboured it, and wrought it fiue or ſixe tymes, ſo that yee bee ſure it is throughlie mingled together, ſo continue labouring it, til it come to a ſmooth paſte, and be well ware at the ſecond opening that ye put not in too much liquor ſodenlie, for then it wil run &amp; if yee take a litle it wil be ſtiffe, and after the ſecond wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it muſt lie a good quarter of an houre, and kéep it warme: then take it vp to the moulding board, and with as much ſpéede as is poſſible to be made, mould it vp, and ſet it into the ouen, of one pecke of flower ye may make ten caſt of Manchets faire and good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>To make ſhort cakes.</head>
                  <p>TAke wheat flower of the faireſt yee can get, and put it in an earthen pot, and ſtop it cloſe, and ſet it in an Ouen and bake it, and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n it is baked, it will be full of clods, and therefore ye muſt ſearſe it through a ſearce: the flower will haue as long baking as a paſtie of Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. When you haue doone this, take clowted creame, or els ſweete Butter, but creame is better, then take ſugar, Cloues, Mace and ſaffron, and the yolke of an Egge, for one doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of Cakes one yolke is enough: then put al theſe foreſaid things together into the cream, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> altogether, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to your flower
<pb facs="tcp:22136:54"/>and ſo make your cakes, your paſte wil be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhort, therefore yee muſt make your cakes very litle: when yee bake your cakes, ye muſt bake them vpon papers, after the drawing of a batch of bread.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>How to make leauened bread.</head>
                  <p>TAke ſixe yolkes of Egs, and a little peece of Butter as big as a Walnut, one handful of veri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fine flower, and make al theſe in paſte, &amp; all to beat it with a rolling pin, til it be as thin as a paper leafe, then take ſwéete Butter and melt it, and rub ouer all your paſte therewith, with a feather: then roll vp your paſte ſoftly as ye would roll vp a ſcroll of paper, then cut them in peeces of three inches long, and make them flat with your hands, and lay them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſhéet of cleane paper, and bake them in an ouen or panne, but the Ouen may not bee too hot, and they muſt bake halfe an howre, then take ſome ſwéete butter and melt it, and put that into your paſte when it commeth out of the Ouen, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are very wet, ſo that they be not drie, take them out of your butter, and laye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a faire diſh, and caſt vpon them a little Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and if you pleaſe, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>namo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ginger, and ſerue them foorth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:22136:54"/>
                  <head>How to make buttered Beere.</head>
                  <p>TAke thrée pintes of Béere, put fiue yolkes of Egges to it, ſtraine them together, and ſet it in a powter pot to the fire, and put to it halfe a pound of Sugar, one penniworth of Nutmegs beaten, one peniworth of Cloues beaten, and a halfe penniworth of ginger bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len and when it is all in, take another pewtec pot and brewe them together, and ſet it to the fire againe, and when it is ready to boyle, take it from the fire, and put a diſh of ſwéet but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into it, and brewe them together out of one pot into another.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="recipe">
                  <head>A Purgation.</head>
                  <p>TAke an ounce of Séene, and as muche of Polipody, bruiſe them, and lay them in ſtéep with a litle Anniſéed, and a litle Ginger, brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in thrée partes of a pinte of white wine, ſo let it lie al a day or a night: then ſeeth it to a quarter of a pinte, and in the morning drink it early.</p>
                  <p>Cancer, Scorpio, and Piſces: theſe thrée bee the beſt ſignes to take purgations in.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="order_of_service">
               <pb facs="tcp:22136:55"/>
               <head>The order howe all maner of meates ſhould be ſerued to the table, with their proper ſawces both for fleſh and fiſh.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>For fleſh daies at dinner.</head>
                  <label>The firſt courſe.</label>
                  <item>POttake or ſtewed broth, Boyled meate or ſtewed meat, Chickens and Bacon, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Béefe, Pies Gooſe, Pigge, roſted Béefe, Roſted veale, Cuſtard.</item>
                  <label>The ſecond courſe.</label>
                  <item>Roaſted Lambe, roaſted Capons, Roſted Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Chickens, Pehennes, Baked Veniſon, Tart.</item>
                  <label>The firſt courſe at Supper.</label>
                  <item>A Sallet, a Pigs Petitoe, powdered Beefe ſliced, a ſhoulder of Mutton or a breaſt, Veale, Lambe, Cuſtard.</item>
                  <label>The ſecond courſe.</label>
                  <item>Capons roaſted, Connies roaſted, Chickens roaſted, Pigions roaſted, Larks roaſted, a Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                  </item>
                  <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:22136:55"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:22136:56"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22136:56"/>
            <head>The table of all the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall matters contained in this booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>TO boile Mutton ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſundry waies fol. 1</item>
               <item>To Boile mutton for a ſick body. fol. 2</item>
               <item>Balles of Mutton. fol. 3</item>
               <item>To boile a Capon with Orenges after miſtres Duffieldes way. ib</item>
               <item>To boile a Capon in white broth foure ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of waies. fol. 3.4.</item>
               <item>Sops for a capon fol. 4.</item>
               <item>Sops for Chickens. fol. 5</item>
               <item>To boil a mallard two ſundry waies. ib</item>
               <item>To boile a Ducke. ib</item>
               <item>To boil Stackdoues ib</item>
               <item>To boile a Conie with a pudding in his belly. fol. 6</item>
               <item>To boile chickens or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons. ib</item>
               <item>To boile chickens three other waies. fol. 6.7</item>
               <item>For to ſéeth hennes and capons in winter in white broth. ib</item>
               <item>To boile calues feete or Lambs feet. ib</item>
               <item>To broile a tripe. ib</item>
               <item>To boil tripes, pigs pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titoes, or Neats feete. fol. 8</item>
               <item>To boile pigs petitoes another way. ib</item>
               <item>To boile chickens after the French. ib</item>
               <item>To boil tripes after the faſhion. ib</item>
               <item>How to make Long worts ib</item>
               <item>Triped mutton. ib</item>
               <item>To boile a Lambs head and purtenance. ib</item>
               <item>To boil quailes. fol. 9</item>
               <item>To ſmere a Conie. ib</item>
               <item>For to make Hodgepote two waies. ib</item>
               <item>To boile a brawne. ib</item>
               <item>To make a good white broth. fol. 10</item>
               <item>Howe to make farts of portingale. ib</item>
               <item>Howe to make fyſtes of portingale. ib</item>
               <item>How to make Frenche pottage. ib</item>
               <item>To make fine pap. fol. 11</item>
               <item>A broth for a weake body ib</item>
               <item>A good way to powder or barrell beefe. ib</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:22136:57"/>
               <item>For to keep Lard three maner o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> waies fol. 11.12.</item>
               <item>How to make Blamieger two wayes. ib.</item>
               <item>To make ſtued broth ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for fleſh or fiſh. fol. 13.</item>
               <item>Stewed ſteakes ib.</item>
               <item>How to ſtuf a capo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> three waies ib.</item>
               <item>To ſtue birds. fol. 14</item>
               <item>To ſtue Larks or Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes. ib.</item>
               <item>To ſtue a Mallard. fol. 14.</item>
               <item>To ſtue a Cocke fol. 15</item>
               <item>To ſtue a Neats foot. ib.</item>
               <item>To make ſtued pottage in Lent ib.</item>
               <item>To ſtue béefe two waies fol. 16</item>
               <item>To make brine to keepe Lard. ib</item>
               <item>For to make Maunger blaunch. ib</item>
               <item>To ſawce a pig. fol. 17</item>
               <item>To make paſt, &amp; to raiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ib</item>
               <item>To ma e fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e paſt two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aies. ib</item>
               <item>To bake veniſon, or mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leed of veniſon. ib</item>
               <item>For to make ſwéete pies of V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ale. fol. 18</item>
               <item>To make Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s four waies. ib</item>
               <item>How to make ſpeciall good pies. &amp;c. fol. 19</item>
               <item>To ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e chickens foure wa es. fol. 20</item>
               <item>To bake a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie ib</item>
               <item>To bake a Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant. ib</item>
               <item>To bake a capon in ſteed o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Feſant. fol. 21</item>
               <item>To bake red Deare. ib</item>
               <item>To bake Veniſon ib</item>
               <item>To bake a Crane or a buttard ib</item>
               <item>To bake a mallard. ib</item>
               <item>To bake a wild boar. fol. 22</item>
               <item>To bake wild Ducks ib</item>
               <item>To bake calues feet two waies. ib</item>
               <item>How to bake a Pig. ib</item>
               <item>How to bake a Pigli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fawne fol. 23</item>
               <item>To bake a Neats tong i</item>
               <item>To bake an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. ib</item>
               <item>To bake a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ammon of bacon. ib</item>
               <item>How to make a rare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit with veale. ib</item>
               <item>A flarenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. fol. 24</item>
               <item>A pie to keep long. ib</item>
               <item>To bake ſmall meats ib</item>
               <item>To make a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in lent. fol. 25</item>
               <item>To make a cuſtarde in Lent. ib</item>
               <item>Howe to bake Oyſters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and all. ib</item>
               <item>To bake peares, quinces
<pb facs="tcp:22136:57"/>and Wardens, ib</item>
               <item>To bake Orenges two waies, fol. 26</item>
               <item>To bake peaches. fol. 28</item>
               <item>How to bake pippins, ib</item>
               <item>To make a cuſtarde two waies, ib</item>
               <item>To make tarts neentéen waies, fol. 29, 30, 31, 32</item>
               <item>Howe to make Allowes of mutton, fol. 32</item>
               <item>To roſt a Gibot of mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. ib</item>
               <item>How to roſt a hare. fol. 33</item>
               <item>To roſt a calues beas ib</item>
               <item>To roſt a capon, feſant or partridge. ib</item>
               <item>How to roſte veniſon, ib</item>
               <item>How to ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te a Quail, ib</item>
               <item>To r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſte a crane, Heron or Bitture ib</item>
               <item>How to roſt a Plouer or S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te. fol. 34</item>
               <item>To roſte woodcocks ib</item>
               <item>To make fine Rice pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, ib</item>
               <item>To make good Lenton Pottage, ib</item>
               <item>To ſeeth a Pike, carp, &amp; Gurnard. ib</item>
               <item>To ſeeth freſh Salmon, Bream, R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ches, F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Eeles, Stockfi h a Dorte or Mullet, fol. 35</item>
               <item>To ſtue herrings, fol. 36</item>
               <item>How to roſte a pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce of Stockfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. ib</item>
               <item>To make hering pies ib</item>
               <item>To bake a carp a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oll of freſh ſalmon, a breame, a gurnard, a tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t. fol. 37</item>
               <item>Howe to make a good Marc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pane. ib</item>
               <item>To make Reſtons, fol. 38</item>
               <item>To make a Vaunt, ib</item>
               <item>For to make Frians, fol. 39</item>
               <item>To make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>we, ib</item>
               <item>To make Gellie fowre ſundrie w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es, fol. 40, 41</item>
               <item>All neceſſaries belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to a banquet, fol. 42</item>
               <item>A t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, ib</item>
               <item>To clari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ib</item>
               <item>To make fillets Gallen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine two waies, fol. 43</item>
               <item>Toſtes of Veale, ib</item>
               <item>An Apple Moye ib</item>
               <item>To make Peſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s two waies, ib</item>
               <item>Pett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſeruices, fol. 44</item>
               <item>Spaniſh bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, ib</item>
               <item>Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of Italie. ib</item>
               <item>Howe to make Almonde butter. &amp;c ib</item>
               <item>To make Ipocras two waies, ib</item>
               <item>Egges vpon ſops, and to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Egs in Lent. ib</item>
               <item>To make caſt cream two waies. fol. 46</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:22136:58"/>
               <item>To make clou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed creame after Miſtre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. fol. 56</item>
               <item>To make creame of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, ib</item>
               <item>A poſſet curd, fol. 47</item>
               <item>Miſtres Drakes way in make ſoft cheeſe, ib</item>
               <item>To make fritters ſir ſun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drie waies, fol. 48</item>
               <item>To make Pancakes, fol. 49</item>
               <item>For to make pudding<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s three waies, ib</item>
               <item>To make a tanſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y three ſeueral waies, ib</item>
               <item>The making of marcher two waies. fol. 51</item>
               <item>To make ſhort cakes, fol. 52</item>
               <item>Howe to make leane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed bread, ib</item>
               <item>To mak butterd bees fol. 53</item>
               <item>A purgation, ib</item>
               <item>The order how al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meats ſhould bee ſerued, with their ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. fol. 54</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:22136:58"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
